<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A martial conference pleasantly discoursed betweene two souldiers, the one Captaine Skil, trained vp in the French and Low Country seruices, the other Captaine Pill, only practised in Finsburie fields in the modern warres of the renowmed Duke of Shordich and the mightie Prince Arthur / newly translated out of Essex into English by Barnabe Rich ...</title>
            <author>Rich, Barnabe, 1540?-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20991.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2298</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23248191</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23248191</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26442</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10710)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26442)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1802:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A martial conference pleasantly discoursed betweene two souldiers, the one Captaine Skil, trained vp in the French and Low Country seruices, the other Captaine Pill, only practised in Finsburie fields in the modern warres of the renowmed Duke of Shordich and the mightie Prince Arthur / newly translated out of Essex into English by Barnabe Rich ...</title>
                  <author>Rich, Barnabe, 1540?-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Iohn Oxenbridge, dwelling in Paules Church yardat the signe of the Parrot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴ K².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Jesus College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26442:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26442:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MARTIAL Conference, Pleaſantly diſcourſed betweene two Souldiers, the one Captaine Skil, trained vp in the French and Low country ſeruices, the other Captaine Pill, only practiſed in <hi>Finsburie</hi> fields in the moderne warres of the renowmed Duke of Shordich, and the mightie Prince Arthur.</p>
            <p>Newly tranſlated out of Eſſex into Engliſh, by Barnabe Rich gentleman, Seruant to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Malui me diuitem eſſe quam vocari.</hi>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <q>LAB<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ET CON<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>STANTIA</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London for Iohn Oxenbridge, dwelling in Paules church yard at the ſigne of the Parrot 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26442:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26442:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt honorable and renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Lord Sir <hi>George Carie,</hi> of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble order of the Garter knight, Baron of Hunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Gouernour and Captaine of the Iſle of Wight, Captaine of her Maieſties Gentlemen Penſioners, Lord Chamberlaine to her Mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>stie, and of her Highneſſe moſt honorable priuie Counſell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleaſed your Honor in fauourable ſort to accept of a firſt croppe of my vnſauourie fruits: vnſauorie I may well call them that come from ſo barren a ſoile, too colde and drie, to nouriſh dainties, or to affoord a pleaſing plant, that may be ſauourie to your Lordſhippes taſte: but the field is yours, your Lordſhip hath purchaſed it, and tied it by band; for euer bound vnto you by ſo many noble fauours, it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your Honor to vouchſafe vnto me: the fruits therefore both of my labours and of my leiſures are due vnto your Lordſhip, and doe appertaine vnto your Honor all by proper right, and euerie man is inclined to accept of his owne, and fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably to regard them, be they neuer ſo ſimple. I
<pb facs="tcp:26442:3"/>haue therefore preſumed to preſent you with a ſecond croppe, not ſo ſeaſonable as they ſhoulde be, by reaſon of mine owne ill husbandry, that can not obſerue that Decorum looked after by Schollers and maiſters of Art and method: yet I hope my errors ſhal paſſe for the eaſier payment, and be the better borne withall, my ſelfe being a martiall Profeſſor; and continually armed to the proofe, with a ſeruiceable and duetifull heart to your Honor, and to that moſt noble and virtuous Ladie, your Lordſhips bedfellow, of whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors I haue taſted, and of whole worthineſſe the leſſe I write, the leſſe I wrong her, and therefore as a ſubiect too high for my conceit to reach vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, I will leaue her to the praiſe of more happie pennes than mine owne, and may ceaſe to write, but neuer to wiſh vnto you both, all honor and happineſſe, that is not preiudiciall to true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, and thus will reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your L. in all humble and dutifull affection
<hi>Barnabe Rich.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26442:3"/>
            <head>To the friendly Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing (friendly Reader) more neceſſary immediatly after the knowledge of God, than to know how to mannage our Martiall cauſes, when it is moſt euident, that aſwell Prince, country, religion, lawe, iustice, ſubiects, and all together, are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the guard and protection of armes, &amp; as the establiſhing of all happy estates, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially conſiſteth, firſt in religion and loue of God, and then in the knowledge and practiſe of Armes, euen ſo as there is nothing amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the religious, more perillous than Sects, ſo amongeſt Souldiers there is nothing more dangerous than to be diuided in opinions.</p>
            <p>The greateſt controuerſie amongeſt vs heere in England, is the diuerſity in opinions concerning the long bow, for that being our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient weapon, and whereby we haue many times preuailed to the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of ſundry notable victories, we are therefore ſtil ſo naturally inclined towardes it, that not onely the multitude and common ſort, whoſe greateſt arguments are fury and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t, but many others that vnder pretence of great experience and skill, will inforce themſelues to defend it, who ranging their paſſions to the tune of reaſon, will many times render ſuch reaſons as are more out of tune than the very paſſions themſelues.</p>
            <p>In this Martiall conference I haue layed downe all the reaſons that I haue heard aledged in the behalfe of bowes, the which I haue done to this purpoſe, that no blinde aſſertions, coloured vnder the pretence of great knowledge, ſhoulde make vs to affie our ſelues in that which is not, nor yet to neglect that, which onely is to be attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto by great practiſe. I haue likewiſe handled ſome other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in a pleaſurable ſort, not of purpoſe to offend any man: and the
<pb facs="tcp:26442:4"/>men that are most vnpatient are ouer contented to take words that are merrily ſpoken, in ſport, for feare leſt other might thinke they would not winch without a galld backe: then how much rather is a dumbe booke to be borne withall, being generally written, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where the title pretendeth matter of pleaſure, and without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, if the Reader bring no offence with him.</p>
            <p>There be ſome that will admit of no bookes, that are not drawne from the very marow and quinteſſence of wit, ſome other againe are better pleaſed with fantasticall and humorous deuiſes: but I vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſlike that fantaſticall humour, that writeth onely for his owne priuate praiſe, and not for ſome profite to others. If thou ſhalt finde me poore in Arte and Science, thou muſt vnderſtand the penne is no part of my profeſſion. And thus not to paſſe the boundes of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, I rest thine in all curteſie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Barnabe Rich.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26442:4"/>
            <head>¶ A Martiall Conference, betweene Captaine Skill and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Pill.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entleman, wel ouertaken, I hope you are riding towardes
<hi>London,</hi> whither my ſelfe am likewiſe trauailing, and would be glad of good company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>I am trauelling towards <hi>London</hi> indéede ſir, and am glad I haue met with ſo good company as your ſelfe doe ſéeme to be, but I pray you ſir, let me craue your name.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill,</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you ſhal vnderſtand that I am by profeſſion a ſouldier, and haue ſerued in the French and Low country ſeruices diuers times, and in ſome other expeditions I haue had charge, and therefore by ſuch as know me, I am called by the name of Captaine <hi>Skill.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Truely ſir, I doe loue you ſo much the better, for I my ſelfe am likewiſe a profeſſor of Armes, and am called by the name of Captaine <hi>Pill:</hi> and therefore I muſt loue ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, nay more, I do reuerence them, nay more yet, I doe honor them: and I beléeue, that on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe ſame occaſion hath now drawne on our acquaintance, and I thinke we goe to <hi>London</hi> both of one arrand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>And I pray you ſir, what might that be as you doe thinke?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Mary I thinke that this muſtering in euerie parte of the realme, and this preparation for the making ready of
<pb facs="tcp:26442:5"/>ſouldiers, is a ſigne of ſame great ſeruice intended, and I thinke of you as I thinke of my ſelfe, that being a noble cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine as I am, you would be glad of imployment, as I wold be, and for that purpoſe you are going vppe to <hi>London,</hi> to make ſute for a company of men, and I promiſe you ſo am I</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>If that be your intent ſir, God ſend you good ſpéed, but in trueth it is no part of my buſineſſe: I neuer yet made ſpeciall ſute for a charge, and I will not beginne now, and yet I haue euermore béene willing and ready to ſerue my Prince and countrie, and ſo I will continue as long as it ſhal pleaſe God to giue me life and abilitie of body. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in theſe dayes, when ſo worthy a Commaunder, ſo noble an Earle doth indeuour himſelfe in his owne perſon, and hath ſo honoured his countrie with his exploites, that all
<hi>Europe</hi> doth ſound out his praiſe: firſt, the magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his minde in vndertaking, his reſolution and proweſſe in performing, his noble and valorous courage in conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, his mercy to the conquered, his incoragement to thoſe that ſerue and follow him, his comfort to the one, his curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to the other, his affabilitie to both, his liberality to all, and his magnificence, as it hath not bin common to Generalles till now of late yeares, ſo in any enterpriſe that hée ſhal vndertake, who would neglect to follow him, that may not onely be ſaid to be <hi>Englands Mars,</hi> but may alſo be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be <hi>Europes Honour?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Skill,</hi> you haue inflamed me, nay you haue mightily inflamed me with an honourable deſire, and although hitherto I neuer made triall of my martiall ſkill before any forraine foe, yet now by the faith of a Souldier I proteſh, that whoſoeuer be the commaunder, or whither ſoener the iourney, if I can get charge, eyther of horſe or of foote, I wil approoue my ſelfe, and wil not tarry behinde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I know not Captaine <hi>Pill</hi> how I might commend your courage, for me thinks I heare you ſay you neuer yet haue incountred with any forraigne foe, I pray you ſir, where haue you then had charge?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Truely ſir I neuer had charge, but once in <hi>Finsbury
<pb facs="tcp:26442:5"/>fields,</hi> in the mightie incounters betweene the renowned Duke of <hi>Shordich,</hi> and the puiſſant Prince
<hi>Arthur,</hi> where I was a Wiſter in the field, and had the command of ſuch a gallant troupe, that if a man had the leading of them ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in
<hi>France</hi> or <hi>Flaunders,</hi> he might be thought a verie vnſkilfull Captaine that could not picke out a thouſande pounds a yeare amongſt them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>You ſhould do wel to procure 150. of them for this expedition which you thinke is now intended: but I pray you ſir, haue you neuer had any other command then this that you haue ſpoken of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Why do you aſke that queſtion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe by your owne wordes you ſhould ſeeme to carrie the title and reputation of a Captaine, againe you ſay, your iourney nowe towardes <hi>London,</hi> is to ſeeke for a charge, nowe both your title and your intent doe argue a farre greater abilitie in you, then you haue hitherto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in your ſelfe, for he is not worthy to be called Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, nor fit to haue a charge, that hath had no better trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning then <hi>Finsburie fields</hi> doth afford.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>But nowe Captaine <hi>Skill,</hi> me thinks you ſkip a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle beyond your ſkill, for if you haue beene of that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in ſeruice as your ſelf doth report of, if you haue not knowne, yet I am ſure you haue heard of Captaines of leſſe practiſe then this that I haue ſpoken of. Why man there be many of our <hi>Regiment,</hi> that are not onely reputed for Captaines by name (as to be called Maſter Captain when they walke vppe and downe in <hi>Poules,</hi> but otherwiſe by meanes of friendes they haue gotten charge indéede) when ſome of them knowe not ſo much as their owne place in the field: but I muſt tell you, you are too preciſe if you will not admitte of this: firſt hee that hath had but the conduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſouldiours (be they more or leſſe) to the water ſide, though he neuer ſerued in the field, yet hee is a Captaine, nay he will be a Captaine, hee that hath but ſeene an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne thrée times ſpread in the field, though he neuer ſawe enſigne of the enemies, he muſt be a Captaine: he that puts
<pb facs="tcp:26442:6"/>himſelfe into the arming doublet, with the poynts with the ſiluer tagges, tied vp in the pitch of the ſhoulder, a ſcarfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his arme, and a feather in his cappe, he ſhal be a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: and he that will gaineſay any of theſe, let him take héede to himſelfe: but to diſhonour a Captaine deſerues no leſſe then a ſtabbe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I know (indéed) that ſome of them are as colericke as the <hi>Brewers horſe,</hi> but you ſhal ſée I wil ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out of their way, and I would be loth to diſhonour them more then they diſhonour themſelues, but is not he to be regiſtred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt your crew of Captaines that will giue money for his charge, and will buy a companie of men, becauſe hee would be a Captaine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Marie ſir I will ſtande to it he is worthie to be a Captaine, for he that hath money in his purſe, and will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſe it to purchaſe a companie of Souldiours, it argues great valew and honeſtie tooin him that will do it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Valure as much as you liſt ſir, but fie vppon that honeſtie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Your reaſon why.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe, if he be an honeſt man that buyeth a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of Souldiours, he ſhall neuer make his money a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>And he is a foole that wil lay out his money to loſſe in this age.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Why then lette vs commend his wit, but not his honeſtie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>It is no matter ſir what you commend or diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, I warrant you they are at a poynt for that: but there are a number of Souldiours noweadayes, who becauſe they haue had a little more training before an enemie, then we that neuer ſaw an enemie, doo therefore thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be ſo priuileged, that they would haue none to be imployed with charge but themſelues, but they are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, for perhaps we haue better meanes for the matter then they, for we haue money to procure friends, and we haue friendes to procure vs charge, when ſometime they ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:26442:6"/>go without.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>And the moſt of them when they haue gotten charge, are as ſkilfull both to deceiue the Prince, and to cooſin the Souldiours, as the proudeſt Captain in <hi>England,</hi> that hath ſerued longeſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Fie Captaine <hi>Skill</hi> I muſt néedes condemne you now, your words doo ſtretch too farre, howe vnſéemely is it for Souldiours to inuey againſt Souldiours: what ſpeake you of deceiuing the Prince, when euerie man doth ſeeke to liue by the Prince? he that hath an office and cannot gain by it, is a foole, and why ſhould not Captaines helpe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues amongſt the reſt? And for the cooſining of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour, what and if a Captaine do now and then gette a crowne out of his Souldiours moneths pay, alas it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, it will ſcarce pay for an ounce of gold lace: and hée that is not gallantly gilded, he is but of the baſeſt ſort of Captaines, and therefore they muſt haue helpes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I haue knowne Captaines that haue worne both golde and ſiluer, without any coſonage or other deceit, either to Prince or Souldiour: and to ſay truly, gold and ſiluer is fitteſt for Captaines, for thoſe that may be ſayde (indéede) to be Captaines of worth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>There are not many of thoſe, for I know verie few Captaines nowadayes that are worth much, and therfore he that will be a Captaine of worth, he muſt learne to ſhift betimes, or it will not be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Pill,</hi> your conſtruction of a Captaine of worth doth ſo commend your Martiall ſkill, that I thinke a man of your experience were more worthie to be made a great officer in the field, then to be ſo meanely imployed in the place of a priuate Captaine, to haue the command but of a hundred and fiftie poore Souldiours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>I tell you Captaine <hi>Skill</hi> my words are myſticall, and not to be conceited by euerie ordinarie Souldiour that is but of a darke &amp; cloudy vnderſtanding, and for this ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency that you finde to be in me, I doe as highly commend your iudgement, that can ſo readily diſcerne it, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:26442:7"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:7"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:8"/>that I haue hitherto hidden my talent, yet now ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many men of leſſe training then my ſelfe, are ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to thruſt themſelues forward, and many times haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained what they thruſt ſo faſt for, I will therefore venture my ſtake amongſt the reſt, for I ſée it is but fortune that ruleth all, vertue helpes little, deſert much leſſe: Captaines are not ſo much appoynted for the knowledge they haue gotten by ſeruice, as for the friendes they are able to make, my Lord he ſpeaks for one, my lady ſhe ſues for another: my Lord commendes his man for his ſtomacke, my Ladie ſhée prayſes her man for his courage: men haue ſkill to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, women muſt not be denied when they ſue, and hée that hath a good ſtomacke and is of a luſtie courage, is fitte to be a Captaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Indéed valiance is a ſpeciall vertue for a Souldier, if theſe men may be ſaide to haue it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Why who will denie it them, or make any doubt but that they haue it? he that hath liued all the dayes of his life at home amongſt his friendes, and neuer ſawe an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie that might hurt him, and now wil make a ſpecial ſute to be a Captaine, and to appoſe himſelfe into ſo many pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils, as he knowes not what they are, nor what they mean: who will denie this man to be valiant?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>No man that is wiſe but will confeſſe him to be as valiant a captaine as euer ran him ſelfe in to danger with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iudgement, or as he that wil leape the hedge before hée hath ſéene the ditch.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Yet there he ſome that will ſaye it is a deſperate kinde of holdnes, and they will call it raſhnes, and fooliſh hardines, then they will make deſtinctions what is true va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance indéed, but theſe diſtinguiſhers are fitter for the ſchoole then for the field.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sill</speaker>
               <p>And I thinke theſe Captaines had neede to go to ſchoole with them, to learne a little wit howe to demeane themſelues when they come to the field.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Why ſhould you thinke ſo, do you imagine that martiall knowledge fit for the fielde is to be learned at a
<pb facs="tcp:26442:8"/>ſchoole?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>And how ſhould he come by that martiall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that neuer came in the field?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>And wherefore doe men ſéeke charge, but becauſe they are willing to learne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Let them firſt learn, to obey, before they take vpon them to commaund.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>It is a baſe minde in a Gentleman to ſerue vnleſſe he may commaund.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>It is a vaine preſumptuous minde in any man to ſéeke to commaund, before he knowes how to commaund.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Do you call it preſumption for a Gentleman t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoure himſelfe to ſerue his Prince and country?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I ſay it is the moſt honourable thing that any gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman can indeuoure, but I cal it preſumption in him that will take vppon him to commaund before he haue experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence how.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>And howe is experience ſooner attained vnto, then for a man to be in place where he may commaund?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>But that experience is at too high a rate, for the vnſkilfull Phiſitian, and the ignorant Captaine do buy their experience with the price of mens liues, and therefore in the olde time there was great regard had in the chooſing of their Captaines, and no man might commaund or haue authoritie, that was vnder thirtie yeeres of age, but <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> amongſt the reſt admitted none to the place of a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that was vnder thréeſcore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>But men were not ſo capable in thoſe days as they are now, for now there be ſome, if they haue but ſéene Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers trayned on
<hi>Mile-end-greene,</hi> or haue borne office in a Midſummer ſight, or haue bin at the fetching home a Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole, they wil by and by put themſelues into the Captaines trayne, and they will looke as big as <hi>Haniball</hi> the great captain of <hi>Carthage,</hi> but he that ſhuld heare their table-talk when they be at their ordinaries, or amongſt ſuch company as knowes them not, but by their owne reportes, would thinke that the nine worthies were but fooles in compariſon
<pb facs="tcp:26442:9"/>of theſe men, they will ſhake off their ſkermiſhes, they wil martiall their battells into ſquares, into triangles, into ſheares, into ſaws, into halfe moones, into ſnailes, into gées, into eſſes, and into more proportions then either <hi>Langius Vygetius,</hi> or <hi>Machiuell</hi> himſelfe did euer knowe of, though he wrote the arte of warre.</p>
               <p>Now for the winning of walled townes, the aſſailing of cittiedales, or the ſcaling of caſtles, what fortification ſo ſtrong, which they will not ſurpriſe, but with diſcharging of two or thrée volies of oathes? And where was there euer Generall, were he neuer ſo noble, that could performe any ſeruice, how honourable ſo euer, which they will not cenſure and ſéeme to controule. In one thing they wil ſay, oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie was neglected, in another they will ſay, aduantage was not taken, heere they wil ſay, diſcipline wanted, there againe, foreſight was not had, this might haue béene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented thus, and that might haue béene done with better ſafetie tother way. Now who can thinke but that theſe men were crept into the very guttes of martiall ſkill, that are ſo ſkilful to finde all manner of faultes, and ſo expert be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in all other militarie practiſe?</p>
               <p>For the new diſcipline, they haue it as freſhly at their fingers endes, as he that firſt founde it out, and they can commaunde with as good a grace. And do but imagine now that I were at a training ſomewhere about <hi>London,</hi> mark how I could behaue my ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Souldiers ranke your ſelues into fiue, drawe forward ſhot, ſo, very well done: now rancke your ſelues into ſixe, double your ranckes on the right hand, again as you were, march on faire and eaſily, double your files on the left hand, open your rancks, cloſe your files.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>No more good Captaine <hi>Pill,</hi> for héere is no body to maintaine the ſkirmiſh but you and I, and it is pittie you ſhould appoſe your ſelfe to perill, where there is no better reſcues at hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>But howe do you like of my commaunde Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Skill?</hi> you ſée now I could do ſomewhat: but ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:26442:9"/>truly, how do you like of it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>There is no man that can diſlike of it, it may paſſe in diſpite of all the pages in the court, but you neuer learned this at
<hi>Finsbury,</hi> I am ſure of that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Whereſoeuer I learned it, no matter for that, you ſee I haue it, &amp; cunning is no burthen, but do you not think my experience ſufficient for the conduct of an hundred and fiftie ſouldiers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and enough to couſin them all of their paye: and nowe I perceiue indéed that yong Captaines are farre more capable then they were in <hi>Alexanders</hi> time, or elſe they would neuer make ſo great ſute to gette charge, but I ſée it is ſkil that leades them vnto it, and I haue heard of ſome of thoſe capable Captaines, in place where they haue béene imployed, that if they haue but once muſtered 100. men, within one moneth after they will not haue 30. and yet I durſt depoſe for them, that if they were brought to a dayes ſeruice, they would performe as great ſkil with that ſmall number, as if they had fiue hundred to commaund.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>I think ſo, and it is no great wonder, for take héed of any man that is once growne ſo capable that he is apt to take any thing, but I will tell you of a Captaine of a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vertue, that was once imployed, I will not tell you the place whither, but it is no great matter though I name you the man, it was Captaine <hi>Flant,</hi> who was ſent with a hundred Souldiours to a place of ſeruice, where he had not ſtayed long, but he reduced his whole hundred of men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a iuſt proportion of fiftéene, beſides his officers, which was a Lieutenant, an Enſigne, a Sergeant, and a Drum. The 15 he reduced into three Squadrons, which was foure to euerie Squadron, beſides the thrée Corporalles.</p>
               <p>For his march, he would lightly ranke them into thrée, and his fiftéene men made iuſt fiue rankes, neuer a man to ſpare.</p>
               <p>For an inſtant of ſeruice, vpon any ground of aduantage, he would bid them to turne their faces on the right or left hand, and then they were imbatteled into a broade
<pb facs="tcp:26442:10"/>ſquare,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ue in front, and thrée in flanke. If vpon the plaine he were inforced to a ſquare battaile, by thruſting in his Enſigne, his number was iuſt ſixtéene, which being drawn into <hi>Maniples,</hi> of foure made a perfect ſquare, euerie of like ſtrength.</p>
               <p>If at any time he were diſpoſed to martiall them into Batalions, he would neuer make aboue three Batalions of his fiftéene men, neither would he admit any more then fiue men to a Batalion, becauſe hee would do all things by proportion and art.</p>
               <p>To ſhew his ſkill in the new diſcipline, hee would ranke his fiftéene men into ſeuen, which made two rankes, and one man to ſpare, then would he bid them to double their rankes on the right hand, ſo then he had iuſt fouretéene in ranke, but where be the files? and this is called the wile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gooſe ranke. Now if they had but turned their faces to the left hand, then the file was fouretéene, but where be the rankes? and now they were drawne into an excellent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, fitte to haue paſſed any ſtraight that had not béene wonderfull narrow.</p>
               <p>This is inough concerning his diſcipline, and now I will tell you how he paſſed a muſter.</p>
               <p>It fell out, that the Lord Deputie, or Generall, or ſome bodie it was that had the chéefe commaunde in that place, would himſelfe be preſent at a generall muſter, where Captaine <hi>Flant</hi> amongſt the reſt, bringing in his muſter role, his officers being firſt called, his Souldiours were now to anſwere to their names.</p>
               <p>There was firſt called <hi>Thomas Tatter,</hi> that had neuer a whole ragge to put vpon his backe, not almoſt ſo much as would hide his taile. Captaine <hi>Flant</hi> (quoth my Lorde) if the reſt of your companie be in as good plight as this, me thinks they ſhuld be able to maintein a great daies march, becauſe they are not peſtered with too much carriage at their backes.</p>
               <p>I warrant you my Lorde (anſwered the Captaine) you ſhall finde them all alike, and I hope your Lordſhip ſhall ſée
<pb facs="tcp:26442:10"/>ſo ſeruiceable a companie, as would be glad to get their pay in any place in Chriſtendome: well paſſe you by <hi>Thomas Tatter,</hi> who is next?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Slim Slatter,</speaker>
               <p>What <hi>Slim,</hi> bare legged and barefooted both? it is not yet a quarter of a yeare agoe ſithence I gaue you twelue pence to buy brooges, but I ſée you haue ſpent your money at the alehouſe: I will tell your Lordſhippe, if this man would not ſometimes take thrée pottes too many, hée were as braue a footeman as euer marcht vppon two bare féete, and I vſe him indeede for my vauntcurrour, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer <hi>Ambuſcados</hi> when I march in
<hi>Bodalia:</hi> well paſſe by <hi>Slim Slatter,</hi> the next.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicholas Needie,</speaker>
               <p>come on <hi>Nicholas,</hi> a moſt dainty ſhot my Lorde, and an excellent marke man, I do value him to be worth foure men for his readineſſe and ſkill: he hath but one fault, and that is, he will neuer carrie any pouder in his ſlaſke, I thinke he would ſell his ſoule for good drinke: paſſe by <hi>Nicholas Needie</hi> to the next.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gilbert Greedie,</speaker>
               <p>a verie luſtie fellow, and a ſpeciall Souldiour, for a ward, or any place fortified: he loues not the fielde, but if he gettes into a towne, you ſhall neuer gette him out againe, till you plucke him out by the eares:
<hi>Gilbert</hi> follow your fellow, and to the next.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tom Trudge,</speaker>
               <p>an excellent ſhot, I had rather haue him on my ſide in the day of ſeruice, then ſixe of the beſt ſhotte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the field, that are not of mine owne companie, hee hath loſt the ſeere of his péece, but wee will haue it amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt the next muſters, paſſe on
<hi>Tom Trudge,</hi> who is next?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dauie Drudge,</speaker>
               <p>a man of a great ſpright, I haue known when he hath ſéene two hundred enemies in view, and he hath wiſht them all faſt bound, both hand and foote, and himſelfe amongſt the thickeſt of them all alone, and had but a browne bill in his hand: well paſſe along
<hi>Dauie,</hi> and to the next.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas Tattell</speaker>
               <p>mine owne countreyman, wee were borne both in a pariſh, and for ſeuen yeres togither, I was
<pb facs="tcp:26442:11"/>ſure once in a month to finde him in a paire of ſtocks, or in a pillorie: but for an able Souldiour, I would not leaue him for tenne other in his place: go along <hi>Thomas,</hi> the next his
<hi>Camirado.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter Pratle,</speaker>
               <p>an excellent ſkilfull Souldier, more fit to leade others then to be commanded by any, he is ſo careful in his conduct, that I dare vndertake he would neuer leade his company (with his owne good will) where they ſhould take any harme: <hi>Peter</hi> follow your Camirado, I do va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue that man for his ſkill to be worth 20 ordinary Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: the next.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohn Dory,</speaker>
               <p>an olde Souldier you may ſée by all his fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture, it will ſcarce hang together with very antiquitie: fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe your fellowes
<hi>Iohn Dory,</hi> to the next.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim Sory,</speaker>
               <p>ſtand forth man: What I thinke thou haſt bin dauncing of
<hi>Friskin</hi> that ſolde for &amp; hath ſolde his hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band for good ale, but I thinke thou haſt ſolde al the clothes from thy backe for good ale: but there treades not a better ſouldier vpon this ground this day, and although he be not very ſumptuous in his apparel, yet I dare vndertake he ſhal ſhoote as farre out of a muſket, as he that is clad in ſattin and veluet: paſſe along <hi>Sim,</hi> who is next?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Laurence Lifter,</speaker>
               <p>a man if it were to fight a combate for a kingdome, and not worth ſo litle as twentie mens pay: but a P. take the Beadles of Bridewell, they haue made him lame of both his armes, but I warrant for his legges, if it come once to running retrait, the proudeſt of them al can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not mend him: paſſe along <hi>Laurence,</hi> to the next.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Simon Shifter,</speaker>
               <p>if I ſhould ſpeake of this man as I know he deſerueth, I might craue patience to take halfe an houres breath. The ſeueral ſeruices that he hath ſéene, aſwel vpon plaines, hilles, dales, ſtreights woodes, groues, thickets &amp; all other groundes of aduantage, the dangers that he hath eſcaped from Conſtables, Headborrowes, and ſuch other that are the common diſturbers of that ſociety, that loues not to medle with her Maieſties Officers, the ſtratagems he hath deuiſed to paſſe watches, wardes and other am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts
<pb facs="tcp:26442:11"/>that hau bin layde to intercept him in his paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, if I ſhould ſpeake particuarly of his peregrinations what he hath ſéene &amp; paſt, you would ſay that if a hundred men ſhould attempt the like, if one eſcaped ſcotfrée, all the reſt would be hanged. But to ſpeake briefly of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the arte Militarie, I ſay he is able to martiall an army of 20000 ſouldiers, to rancke them into any fit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of bataile, either for the encounter in the fielde, or for the aſſault of a breach, to quarter them, to encampe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to bring them before any fortification, to plant them, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench them, nay, what can he not do that I my ſelfe can do? And what are an hundred ordinary ſouldiers to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a man of his ſeruice?</p>
               <p>Héere the Gouernour interrupting Captaine <hi>Flant,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of him how many there were yet in his roule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde to be called, the Captaine anſwered there were yet thrée, then ſaid the Gouernour that maketh iuſt 15. men by the poule, but as you haue rated them, ſome one man to be worth foure, ſome other ſixe, ſome ten, ſome twentie, and now this laſt you ſay at a hundred, by this reckoning you haue muſtered already aboue an hundred &amp; fiftie, and you haue pay but for one hundred, me thinks you do hinder your ſelfe mightilie to keep fifty or thréeſcore men more then you haue pay for.</p>
               <p>My good Lorde (ſaide the Captaine) I would be loth to couſen my Prince, by taking her pay for a hundred, but I would bring her ſixe ſcore to the hundred, if I want of my number by poule, as it may ſéeme now I want a few, yet if theſe that I haue be duely conſidered of according to their worthines (that are all of them eſpecial choice men) I hope her Maieſtie may wiſh ſhe had more ſuch Captaines, that ſo regardefully doth tender her ſeruice.</p>
               <p>But ſaide the Gouernour, your men do make no ſuch ſhewe as you do commend in them, for there is not any one amongſt them that hath a good garment about him, nor almoſt a paire of ſhooes to his féet. O my Lorde (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the Captaine) that is but their owne humilitie, they
<pb facs="tcp:26442:12"/>cannot abide any pride, fie vpon it; and fie vpon theſe gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded garments, theſe fethers and ſcarffes, they cannot abide them.</p>
               <p>But how now Captaine <hi>Skill?</hi> me thinkes you are halfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſléep, while I haue beene muſtring of an hundred men, and yet haue paſt but twelue by the powle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>You are deceiued Captaine <hi>Pill,</hi> I am not aſléepe; nay I am not ſo much as drowſie, for all this while that you haue ſéene me thus ſilent, I haue bin learning of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<hi>Flant,</hi> firſt the martiall ſkill that he vſed in his order and diſcipline, then the gallant ſhewe of ſelected Souldiers that he brought to the muſters: but eſpecially his fidelitie to her Maieſtie, that would take pay for an hundred and ſerue her with fifteene, a great argument of his dutifull care.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>but you muſt conſider of his ſouldiers, what choice men they were, what ſpeciall ſkill they had, and therefore how to be eſtéemed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>That is a matter indéed of great conſideration, a very choyce company, ſome choſen from the ſtockes, ſome from the pillory, ſome from Bridewel, ſome I think from New gate, and all fit for Bedlem.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>And why ſhould you thinke them to be fit for Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Who were he that ſhould ſée them ſo betottered, &amp; betorne, but would rather thinke them to be mad men then ſouldiers? but how was Captaine <hi>Flant</hi> himſelfe, I hope he was better ſuted for a Captaine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>You may be ſure Captaine <hi>Flant</hi> wanted no ſutes that was fit for a Captaine, and I wil not giue a penny for a captaine nowadayes that is not al to be gilded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>And two pence apéece were a great deale more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome of them be worth, when they haue gilded themſelues as well as they can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>You would make lowe prizd captaines, and I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue we ſhould haue captaines dogge cheape, if you might haue the rating of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I promiſe you I would value them by their expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience,
<pb facs="tcp:26442:12"/>not by their apparell, by their déedes, not by their wordes, for the Corniſh diamond doth ſhine, yet but a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, and the bray of an Aſſe is no leſſe hideous to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple than the roare of a Lion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Theſe are fowle compariſons, and great indignitie to the reputation of Captaines to be made Counterfeites, or to be reputed for Aſſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Pil,</hi> you miſtake your text, I would bée loth to preiudice a captains page by my ſpéeches, much leſſe therefore his maiſter: and is the perfect diamond the leſſe to be eſtéemed of, becauſe it is ſometimes counterfeited? or may not a man ſay, an aſſe is but an aſſe, though he be wrapt in a lions ſkinne, without any offence to the lion himſelfe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>But I ſpeake of no cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfets, I ſpeake of captains, ſuch as haue had charge, and haue had the leading of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the field.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>And I ſpeake of no captaines that can either leade or commaund with ſkill, I ſpeake but of counterfeits, that can doe neither of both, and yet wil take vppon them to be captaines.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pil</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tel what thoſe differences be that you wold ſéeme to make betwéene captaines and captaines, but I call him a captaine that hath had charge in the field, and I think him to be ſkilfull enough, that hath courage enough to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with his enimie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>Then Iacke may be a Gentleman, becauſe he hath beſtrid my lord Maiors mule, but ſet a ſoole on horſe backe, and he wil either catch a fall, or ride his horſe out of breath: and for the corage that you ſpeake of, who is ſo bold as blind bayard? But becauſe you ſay you doe not vnderſtand what the differences ſhould be that I ſhould make betwéene cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and captaines, I am contented to acquaint you with thus much what it is that I meane.</p>
               <p>There is no eſtate, be it empire, kingdome, or other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth whatſoeuer, that may be ſaide to be eſtabliſhed or ſurely ſetled, either from forraine inuaſion or inteſtine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, which is not ſtrengthned, ſtaid, vpholden, and prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="tcp:26442:13"/>vp by force of armes. This was the cauſe that
<hi>Salomon,</hi> who in the holy ſcriptures is called <hi>Rex pacificus,</hi> and was ſtil buſied with the building of the holy Temple, forgat not yet to furniſh his garriſons with expert men of warre, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and charriots, neither hath there béene any well gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued commonwelth, which hath neglected this care, but they haue béene at all times, in all ages, and in all places eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally prouident in this behalfe.</p>
               <p>It would be tedious for me to deliuer, how chéereful they haue béene in incouraging, how liberal in rewarding, how induſtrious in training, how diligent in inſtructing and pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctiſing of men to inable them with ſkill, and to make them expert in the knowledge and feates of war, when they were not ignorant, but would alwayes acknowledge, that both prince, country, life, libertie, goods, law, iuſtice, religion, and all together, depended in the ſkil of the ſouldier, and the knowledge of armes.</p>
               <p>If the matter be of this importance, can you blame prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that haue euermore béene ſcrupulous in the appointing of their armies, and would neuer admit of any to be condue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, leaders, and commaunders, but ſuch as by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and practiſe were found to be of approoued ſkil, and of tried and knowne experience, and not to peſter their ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons with yonglings of little wit and leſſe vnderſtanding, who, becauſe they haue ſéene ſouldiers alittle trained and made ready, or perhappes haue ſerued ſome moneth or ſixe wéekes where they might ſée alittle, wil vpon this preſume to thruſt themſelues into charge, fooliſhly taking vpon them that they are not able to performe, when by the indiſcretion of ſuch a captaine a whole army may be ouerthrown, which may concerne no leſſe than the ſubuerſion of a kingdome, and the loſſe of a princes crowne.</p>
               <p>The matter therefore is not lightly to be regarded, thogh I do not amplifie and inforce it as I could, and her Maieſtie hath payed dearely for the ſeruice of ſome of theſe haſly mad captaines, in ſome places I could name, if I were diſpoſed to inferre preſidents: but letting this paſſe, if for the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:26442:13"/>of a ſéely occupation no leſſe than ſeauen yéeres, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſhip is required, before a man may be thought ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in ſkill or admitted to trade, how happeneth it then that in the Arte Militarie, wherein there was neuer man ſo wel practiſed (no though he had ſerued ſeuen times ſeuen yeares) which was not yet to ſéeke, and euerie day to learne, and yet nouices that haue not bene of ſeuen moneths practiſe, nay ſometimes not of ſeauen wéekes training haue béene thruſt into charge, that hath neither ſkil nor ſcience to command, no nor to performe the leaſt duty that appertaineth to a cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of vnderſtanding.</p>
               <p>It is not enough for a man that ſhall haue charge, to march before his company with a feather in his cappe, and a gilt leading ſtaffe in his hand, not althogh he haue daring enough in him to bring his men to a hot incounter, for For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune is in nothing more variable than in the action of war, and more victories haue béene loſt for want of ſkill, than for want of ſtrength or corage: but if it be true that he that hath courage enough may be thought to haue ſkil enough, it were happy for our Engliſh nation, that are generally a people of ſo great courage and valure, as they are not agaïne to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with the like, and yet euermore ouer reached by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, ſometimes with the barbarous Iriſh.</p>
               <p>The Captaine therefore that relieth ſo much in his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage without ſkill, is like a blind man in a dangerous paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and thinketh ſcorne to be led: for although that cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage be an eſpeciall ornament, wherewith a Captaine ſhould be iudued, yet courage without ſkill is not true va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, but rather may be ſayde to be raſh and fooliſh hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for ſo it hath euer beene defined by the wiſe men of the world.</p>
               <p>That courage (ſaith <hi>Cicero</hi>) that is forward to danger without iudgement, may rather beare the name of lewd hardineſſe, then of manlineſſe: The want of knowledge bréedeth the want of ſkill (ſayth <hi>Xenophon:</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayth, a wiſe man is euer ſtrong, a man of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding increaſeth in ſtrength. And
<hi>Cato</hi> preſcribeth thrée e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall
<pb facs="tcp:26442:14"/>ſpeciall vertues that ought to be in a Captaine, that is to ſay, Experience Policie, and Valiance.</p>
               <p>Here you may ſée, that although Valiance be a ſpeciall ornament for a Captaine, yet it martheth in the rereward, preferring the other twoo as more worthie, for it is not i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the valiant man to do what he can, but hee muſt likewiſe take héede that he attempt nothing but what hée ought, and therefore without experience he ſhal runne into many errors, and where Valiance ſerueth onely but for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, Policie is he that prepareth the meane.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>But me thinks Captaine <hi>Skill,</hi> you are ſomewhat too nice in mincing of this word Valiance, which I do take to bee a naturall gift, but you would ſeeme to couple it I know not to what ſkill, and would admitte of no man to be valiant, that were not almoſt as wiſe as
<hi>Solomon.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>It I haue bin too nice in the mincing of my words, they are the fitter for your queaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie ſtomacke, which I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue to be neither of ſounde diſgeſtion, nor of ſauorie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, for although I do not thinke that euerie va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant man muſt neceſſarily be almoſt as wiſe as <hi>Solomon,</hi> yet of this I can vndoubtedly aſſure you, that there was neuer foole that might be ſayde to haue any valiance at al,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>But I ſpeake not of extremities, for ſay that a braue and gallant minded Gentleman would couragiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take a charge vpon him, though he neuer in his life had ſerued before an enemie, whereby to attaine to any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, may not this man yet be eſteemed for valiant? or would you not putte ſome difference betwéene him and a foole?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>Iuſt as much difference as is betweene a gréene Gooſe and a goſling, and for his valiance you do partly know my minde: but you ſay that I haue alreadie minced the word ouer nicely, but I wil mince it a little better, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would be loath you ſhoulde hurt your teeth in ſhe chewing.</p>
               <p>Valiance is a vertue that fighteth for equitie and iuſtice, for nothing may be holden for honeſt, that is voyde of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb facs="tcp:26442:14"/>and as that knowledge, ſkil, or. policie, that is ſeuered from iuſtice, is rather called ſubtiltie then wiſedome, and in his beſt account is eſtéemed but for craft and deceit, ſo that courage that is forward to danger, more for vain glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and greedie deſire, then for a common profite and a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall good, is rather to be termed deſperate boldneſſe then valiance.</p>
               <p>There is nothing therefore more inciting to true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian valiance, then when a man ſhall remember he goeth to fight in a iuſt and honeſt cauſe: for when I know I ſhall aduenture my life in the maintenauce of Gods true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in the ſeruice of my Prince, or defence of my country, whether I liue or die, in this caſe I may liue or die in the ſeruice and feare of God: my quarrel is good, here is no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſiue to my conſcience, that may diſmay or terrifie me, and therfore I will adde thus much more, there is no man may be ſaid to be truely valiant indeede, that is not truely reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and hath the feare of God before his eies: for which cauſe <hi>Machiuell</hi> the diuels politician, in his politike Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, thinketh that it is not conuenient for a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, to be ouermuch inclined to religion, becauſe (ſayth he) if he be too zealous, it might inféeble his courage: but the Captaines that he thus inticeth, be ſuch as he other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe induceth to all manner of fraude, deceit, and iniurie, neither to make conſcience of their quarrell, nor by what meanes they oppreſſe, ſo they may ouercome, for he knewe well inough, that if there were any feeling in them of true religion, that it would be a checke to their ambition and pride, and thereby an abatement of their harebraind raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which by them is called courage and valiance.</p>
               <p>But let <hi>Machiuell</hi> go, and the reſt to beare him compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, that do thinke that Chriſtian valiance conſiſted other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then in the maintenance of iuſtice and right, or that a man may be ſaid to be truely valiant, that hath no reſpect to the equitie of his cauſe, nor remorſe to his God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Why then you grant that the Captaine that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth God may yet be valiant, though hee be vnſkilfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:26442:15"/>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>If you will grant againe, that if a Captaine fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth God as he ſhould, he would rather be vncaptained, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be a conducter of men to the ſlaughter by his vnſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Skill</hi> you do ouer reach me, but you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcaptaine vs thus, for we will be captaines and haue charge too, ſay you what you liſt, or the beſt friends that wee haue ſhall faile vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>It ſhal neuer offend mee, I will ſtill wiſh that your ſeruice may prooue but halfe ſo beneficiall to the Prince, as I doubt not but you will make it profitable to your ſelues, and I warrant your friendes may then haue greater ioy of your preferment, then hope of any hurt that you will do to an enemie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>In good faith captaine <hi>Skill</hi> you are too preciſe, you are vp with your iuſtice, equitie, good conſcience, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell what: I tel you captaine <hi>Skill,</hi> it is more preacher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like then ſouldierlike: then you would cram more religion into one captaine then would ſuffice for thrée or foure ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men, it is better for a man (in this age) to be wiſe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, then to be ſo ful of zeale as you would haue him, and I tell you for my part I am iuſt of his religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that hauing ſeueral daughters, would not ſticke to marry one to a papiſt, and another to a proteſtant: and I tell you againe they are no fooles that are of that religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Pill,</hi> holde you ſtill in that tract, for you are nowe in the right hie way to promotion, and you may perhaps get an office when it ſhal fall, and therefore cling faſt to that religion, for I tell you it is full of policie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>If it be ſo ful of policy, it is the fitter for mee that am a Captaine, for I heard you ſay, that policie was one of the three eſpeciall vertues, that <hi>Cato</hi> would haue appertinent to a Captaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>But in theſe daies there are many things, that do paſſe vnder the title of policie, that in <hi>Catoes</hi> time they would haue called flat knauery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>But I ſpeake of the time as it is nowe, and you ſay
<pb facs="tcp:26442:15"/>there be two vertues more, that <hi>Catoes</hi> Captaynes muſt be inſpired with, and that is Experience and Valiance.</p>
               <p>Now for experience, though I haue it not in ſuch a forme of perfect diſcipline for the martialling of men, as I thinke <hi>Cato</hi> ſpeaketh of in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> place, yet I haue one principle, which being wel obſerued, may ſtand a Captaine in as much ſtead for his profit and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, as any experience <hi>Cato</hi> could preſcribe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>May I craue of you what principle that might be?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>A matter of nothing among friends, but yet for him that is crept into a charge, &amp; would be glad to make ſome gaine by his company, he muſt in no wiſe thinke that bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery is ſinne, or whatſoeuer he thinkes, let him be ſure that he neuer open his lips to ſpeake againſt it,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Perhaps you think that the Clerke of the Chequer would ſometimes be angry with that Captain that ſhould ſpeake againſt bribery, and that would be the worſe for him when he ſhould paſſe his muſters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Perhaps I did not ſo much as thinke of the Clerke of the Chequer, but take this for a maxime, he that knowes both how to giue, &amp; how to take a bribe, may run through any affaires whatſoeuer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>If you be ſo ſure as you make ſemblance, wée wit ſet it downe, <hi>Probacum eſt.</hi> And now for Policie and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience I perceiue you are very well furniſhed, but what ſay you now for Valiance?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>He that will ſay I am not valiant, ſwoones I will giue him the ſtabbe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Why is that ſuch an argument of valiance, to ſtab a man ſodainly before he be prepared to make defence?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Yea marrie is it ſir, &amp; you may eaſily know a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, if he be of any gallant courage euen by that ſame worde ſtabbe, for that muſt be ſtill at his tongues end, then he muſt haue change of oathes, (for that is a wonderfull grace to a valiant man) and to thruſt them from him as if he would make his audience to tremble, and heauen it ſelfe to ſhake but with the very breath of his diſpleaſure.
<pb facs="tcp:26442:16"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:16"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:17"/>Theſe be infallible arguments of a valerous minde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed, but you would tye valiance to iuſtice and conſcience, and I cannot tell what: but what affinity hath valiance with iuſtice &amp; conſcience? the one is fit for the kings bench, the other for the Chancerie, and what haue ſouldiers to do, with matters of iuſtice, when you ſhall neuer ſee a Iuſtice of peace, that with his good will doth loue to come amongſt them in place where they are?</p>
               <p>Now for conſcience, I thinke there is no man ſo vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that hath not a ſpeciall care of it, and I beléeue (for the greateſt number) of as good remorce as the wolfe that went to ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> to be ſhriuen, who hauing made a ſorrowfull confeſſion of his ſinnes, was inioyned by his ghoſtly father for penance, to faſt twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty foure houres, during which ſpace, he might eate no more meate then in his conſcience was worth aboue three halfe pence, the Wolfe going homeward met in the way with an ewe and her lamb, and being very hungry, yet hauing reſpect to his conſcience (as the prieſt had inioyned him) valewed the ewe to be worth a peny, and the lambe to be worth a halfepeny, and thus did eat them vp both with a good conſcience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Well Captaine <hi>Pill</hi> I would that woluiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience were not in their boſſomes that can do more hurte in <hi>England,</hi> then a hundred thouſand ſouldiers are able to doo in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>A hundred thouſand ſouldiers were able for to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne all
<hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>But a hundred of thoſe wolues were able for to ſpoyle all
<hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>And hée that wil make himſelf a ſhéep, it is no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter though the wolues do eate him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>But theſe wolues are able to make Iack a napes a ſhéepe, a wiſe man a foole, and a foole a wiſe man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe are metamorphoſing Wolues, but can they not make knaues honeſt men?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>That they wil neuer do, but they wil ſooner make honeſt men knaues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:26442:17"/>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Let thoſe woolues go to the gallowes for me, and let not vs that are ſouldiers ſéeme to contend y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> one againſt the other, but let vs learne of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>What would you haue vs learne of them, to goe to the gallowes with them do you meane?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Let them goe to the gallowes by themſelues that haue deſerued it, and let vs learne of them to be wiſe, let vs learne of them to thriue and helpe our ſelues, and lets learne of them to runne ſmoothely through the world, for thoſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes I warrant you can bite when they do not barke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>An ill condition that ſame, for I remember a fooliſh tale of a noble man ſometimes here in <hi>England,</hi> who bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mallice to a poore gentleman that dwelt not farre from him, did by many meanes ſo couertly and ſlily wring and oppreſſe him, that the poore Gentleman, finding howe the game went, thought it beſt to ſéeke vnto him, and with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſiue ſpéeches beſought his lordſhip, not to ſtand gréeuous vnto him, proteſting that he had neuer offended him to his knowledge, but would be glad to tender vnto him any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice that might be fauourably accepted of.</p>
               <p>Why (quoth my lord) what ſhould make you to vſe theſe ſpéeches vnto me? My good lord (anſwered the other) I do finde my ſelfe to be croſſed and hindered by many meanes, and I do vndoubtedly know that it is your lordſhips diſple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure borne vnto me, that doth thus ouer-burthen me.</p>
               <p>Why then (ſaide the noble man) if you do finde your ſelfe ſo ouerborne by me, you ſee then I can bite, though I barke not.</p>
               <p>I do ſée it, and féele it (my good Lord, anſwered the other) but I proteſt, if I had a dogge that were of that qualitie, I would hang him as ſoone as euer I came home.</p>
               <p>And I promiſe you captaine <hi>Pil,</hi> I am of this Gentlemans minde, I do not like of theſe flearing curres, that will firſt fawne in a mans face, and after bite him by the ſhinnes, I woulde ſuch curres were hanged (ſay I) and theſe baſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours of all others, are vnfitting for ſouldiers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pil</speaker>
               <p>I pray you captaine <hi>Skil,</hi> what is it that you do think
<pb facs="tcp:26442:18"/>to be beſt befitting for a ſouldier?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>I haue already tolde you, there is nothing more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable in a ſouldier than true chriſtian valiance, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling all particular affectations (with inuincible courage) fighteth but only for equity and right, for what can be more bleſſed then this iuſtice and right, whereby we reſraine all iniurie and wrong, giuing to euery one what to him apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pil</speaker>
               <p>But you ſtand vpon the etymologie of wordes, and you would make Valiance to be but a deriuatiue, drawing it from Iuſtice, Conſcience, Religion, and I wot not what, but if your diſtinctions be of worth, I know but a few cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines in <hi>England,</hi> that may be ſaide to be valiant, and that were an ill turne for her Maieſtie when ſhée ſhould haue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to imploy them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay I woulde deriue Valiance from Iuſtice, Conſcience, Religion, and you knowe not what, but you would deriue it from ſtabbing, ſwaſhing, ſwearing, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and it makes no matter what: but for valiant Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, no doubt but her Maieſtie is better prouided than your vnderſtanding doth ſerue to conceiue of, if not, ſhée might pay dearely for it in the time of ſeruice, for what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe might be hoped for by theſe warres, that are ſupplyed by men altogether irreligious, prophane, godleſſe, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vnſkilful withal: far be it from her Maieſties thoght, to put her truſt in thoſe men that haue neither truſt nor fear of God, or to commit her quarrel to their fortunes, whome God hath not promiſed to bleſſe, but hath confidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt them his malediction and curſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pil</speaker>
               <p>Without doubt (captaine <hi>Skil</hi>) you do too much ouer runne your ſelfe, your words do rubbe a great many Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen ouerthwart the ſhins more than you are aware of: what and if a Gentleman ſometimes, of a braue and luſtie courage ſhould ſweare half an houre together by the clocke? a wiſe concluſion I promiſe you, that for ſwearing of two or thrée dozen of oathes, a man ſhould therefore be condemned to be irreligious, prophane and godleſſe, a prettie ieſt, fitter
<pb facs="tcp:26442:18"/>for a foole to ſporte at, than for a wiſe man to beléeue, and for theſe fellowes that prate ſo much of religion, that haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for an othe but, yes verily, and no truely, and I pray you ſweare not, truſt ſuch a one he that liſteth, but I can tel you what you ſhall finde of him: but away with the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, and giue me him that cannot diſſemble, who ſpeaking what he thinketh, wil ſweare what he ſpeaketh: here is no double dealing, this man hath neither falſhoode forged in his tongue, nor paſſion ſmothered in his heart, but his words, his oathes, his countenaunce, his demeanour, and all his whole gouernement, ſhal bewray and lay open, howe hée is affected, to what he is inclined, and whereunto hée is diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>But for a man to expreſſe his anger in a milde and ſoftly maner, it is more Meacocke-like than Souldier-like, howe diſgraceful were it for a captaine vpon any diſcontentment, when he ſhould thunder forth his furie, &amp; that with ſuch hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour as the heauens ſhould tremble at the very eccho of his oathes, but neglecting this captaine-like demeanour, as though he were halfe afraide, will pinch me foorth an oath; ſwearing like one of the Quéens ſilke women, now by gods dainty deare, I will not diſgeſt ſo great indignitie, and by cocke and pie, I will be reuenged of the iniurie.</p>
               <p>How ill beſéeming were this for a Souldier? but moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and lothſome for a captaine: but theſe thréedbare oths are moſt fit for thréedbare fellowes, and let ſouldiers ſhew themſelues in all their demeanours, lik men, and not like meacockes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>Without doubt captaine <hi>Pill,</hi> you haue ſpoken as wel in the commendation of ſwearing, as if you had béene a graduate in that profeſſion: but yet for the courage that you would thereby attribute to thoſe that doe vſe it, it is like the commendation that a noble mans foole did ſometimes giue to a merchant of London in the praiſe of his wiues ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, which (as I remember) fell out in this manner:</p>
               <p>A noble man that was inuited by a merchant of London to a dinner, brought with him a foole, who being but a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<pb facs="tcp:26442:19"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:19"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:20"/>was yet ſo ful of ſport (which pleaſed ſo well his Lorde and maiſter) that he woulde neuer haue this foole from his héeles: and comming to the merchants houſe, he founde a great Ape that was tied in a chaine without in the courte, with whome the foole incountering, the Ape amongſt our newfangled fellowes, was not to learne, but had gotte the Mop, the Mowe, the Mump, the Nod, the Shrug, the Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les mains, the Congée, and all the reſt of thoſe graces; that are vſed by our Fantaſtikes in theſe dayes.</p>
               <p>And the foole againe, hee could dowke with the Friar, looke aſkaunce with the Phyſitian that were caſting of a womans water, grinne with the yong heire that had late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buried a miſerable father, gape with him that waited for a benefice, frowne with him that was chaunced ſixe and ſeauen and all to ten, yet loſt both by and maine: to be ſhort, he could change his lookes, and make as many madde faces as he that takes Tabacco.</p>
               <p>This glée betwéene the Foole and the Ape made the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany mery, but ſpecially my lord who laught heartily to ſée the gréeting and entertainment that was betwéene them: at the laſt, the foole turning to the goodman of the houſe, aſked of him, who that ſame was that he had ſo tied vp, whom the marchant anſwered, that it was one of his boyes: nowe by my troth (ſaid the foole) it is a very pretty boy, and I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant him, it he liue, he wil prooue a very good fellow.</p>
               <p>Thus leauing the Ape, they were no ſooner entred into the Merchants houſe, but the Foole eſpied a great Munkie. What ſaide the foole to the merchant, is this another of thy boyes? Yea mary is it Robin (ſaid the marchant) this is an other of my boies, and as honeſt a man as the other, though he be ſomewhat yonger. Well (ſaide the foole) I warrant thée thou haſt an honeſt woman to thy wife: Why ſo Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin (ſaid the marchant) how knoweſt thou that? It muſt needes be (ſaid the foole) thy boyes be all of them ſo like thy ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Nowe I can not ſée but that this commendation thus gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, doth as fitly concerne the womans honeſtie, as the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:26442:20"/>you haue ſo much indeuoured, may concerne any mans corage or valiance, for the babes that you ſo much ſet forth, they are but like the marchants boyes, this ſwearing, this ſtaring, and this blaſpheming, which you woulde haue ſo captaine like, they are all but Apes and Munkies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pil</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tel (captain <hi>Skil</hi>) what conſtruction I ſhuld make of your hiſtorie: but I hope you doe not meane to giue me the foole by circumſtance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>I hope (captaine <hi>Pil</hi>) I ſhal not néede to do that, for if you were thorowly acquainted with me, you would ſaie there were no circumſtance in me.</p>
               <p>You ſay you profeſſe Armes, and I am contented to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue you, you take vpon you to be a captaine, yet you neuer had charge but in <hi>Finsbury fields,</hi> you thinke that any man that is valiant is fit to haue conduct, &amp; you cannot tell what true valiance meaneth. Once againe therefore I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to tell you, euery vertue hath his counterfeit follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for as deceit, ſometimes créeping in is called Pollicie, ſo Raſhnes ſhrowdeth it ſelfe vnder the title of Fortitude: and as it is true, that all valiant men are hardy, ſo it is likewiſe as true, that all hardy menne are not valiant: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore briefly to conclude, he is not truely ſaide to be valiant, that is not firſt ſtrengthened by God, and fortified againe by his owne ſkil and knowledge.</p>
               <p>Now concerning Captaines, it is not the place of a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that dignifieth the vnworthy perſon, who is not able to execute it, but it is the worthineſſe of him that is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the place, that dignifieth and renowneth the rowme.</p>
               <p>The title of Captaine hath béene an honourable reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is now growne to be a matter of ſcorne to be called Captaine, when ſo many baſe and vnworthie perſons will néedes march vnder that title, that knoweth not the leaſt duty that appertaineth to a Captaine.</p>
               <p>The antiquity would neuer admit of any Captaine that was either inſufficient in ſkill, or openly detected for vice: ſwearing bréedeth hatefulneſſe to al honeſt eares, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe extorting both of Prince and Souldier, pride bringeth
<pb facs="tcp:26442:21"/>with it diſdaine: but how odious a thing it is to ſée a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine himſelfe to be glittering in golde, and to ſée his poore ſouldiers to followe with no hoſe to their legges, nor ſhooes to their feete.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cato</hi> being Cenſurer to make choyſe of a General in the Panonian wars, openly diſgraced and diſmiſſed <hi>Publiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> becauſe hee had ſéene him walke the ſtréetes of <hi>Rome</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed.</p>
               <p>And as they were thus preciſe in the choyſe of their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, ſo they were as héedefull, not ſuffering them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into vnlawfull actions, that were voyde of iuſtice, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, or pietie: they puniſhed nothing with more ſeueritie then thoſe enterpriſes that were either attempted againſt commaundement, or vndertaken againſt reaſon: but as they puniſhed thoſe victories that were attained by lewd and fooliſh hardineſſe, ſo miſfortune diminiſhed not his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, that attempted with diſcretion, neither attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting cowardlineſſe to ill ſucceſſe, nor valiance to good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
               <p>The campe in thoſe dayes was a ſchoole of honour, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, obedience, dutie, and loyaltie, but now a denne of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, trecherie, théeuerie, robberie, and all manner of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie.</p>
               <p>But if this regard in the chooſing of captaines were v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the antiquitie ſo many yeares agoe, when armies vſed to appoynt the field, &amp; when their whole forces were brought to an incounter, where the weakeneſſe of a cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine might be the better borne withall, where there were ſo many ſuperior officers to direct him, howe much more rather ſhould we be more circumſpect in theſe dayes, in the appoynting of our captaines, when his ſkill and knowledge doth not onely concerne the ſafetie or loſſe of many mens liues, (which euerie good captaine ſhould preferre before the killing of his enemies) but eſpecially ſeruice ſtanding now as it doth, moſt comely in ſkirmiſhes, where the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine is not holpen, but with the aduantage of his owne experience? I wonder therefore how ſo many inſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:26442:21"/>men dare oppoſe themſelues to vndertake a matter of ſo great importance, where their want of knowledge may ſometimes be the occaſion of too much raſhneſſe, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time againe leade them into timeritie and want of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, which may concerne no leſſe then the loſſe of all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>You ſay there is no circumſtance in you, and then your plaine meaning muſt follow thus, you would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any man to haue conduct, but he that hath experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and I am contented to allow you that, but here is the matter, you thinke no man can attaine to this experience, that hath not ſerued in <hi>Flanders</hi> or in <hi>France:</hi> you ſay I haue ſerued but in <hi>Finsburie fields,</hi> and you ſée me to make but a trifle of that: but captaine <hi>Skill,</hi> to deale without cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, as you ſay you haue done with me, and to tell you in as plaine termes as you haue told me, I thinke you do not know from whence experience growes, nor where it is to be ſought for, you thinke no where but in <hi>Flanders</hi> or in <hi>France,</hi> but ſir, you are deceiued, neither is it long train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and much exerciſe that makes euerie man fitte to bee a captaine, although there is no man ſo vnapt, but with vſe is made more perfect: but that experience that is fitte for a captaine, and that is worthie to carrie the credite of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall ſkill (indéede) is to be attained vnto without croſſing the ſeas, nay, without any manner of training at all, and that by two eſpeciall meanes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I pray you lets heare the firſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>The firſt is, when almoſt euerie ordinarie about
<hi>London</hi> may be ſayde to be an <hi>Academie</hi> of martiall ſkill, where many times thoſe captaines that are of our <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſhall ſpende you the whole mealetide, be it dinner or ſupper, with nothing but martiall diſcourſes, dilating of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, of orders, of lawes, of diſciplines, of ſtratagems, of watching, of warding, of charging of retyring, of offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, of defending, of winning, of looſing, of approaching, of ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing, and you ſhall neuer heare them but they will ſtill conclude with victorie, and therein conſiſteth their ſkill,
<pb facs="tcp:26442:22"/>that they will euermore be conquerours, they will neuer looſe by any miſfortune, and yet but in one dinners diſcourſe they will ſettle the king of <hi>France</hi> into a quiet gouernment, they wil baniſh the Spaniards from out the low countries, they wil reforme
<hi>Ireland,</hi> they wil thruſt the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> cleane out of
<hi>Portingall,</hi> they wil take from him his <hi>Indies,</hi> and they will not forget to eate their meate, and to drinke thrée or foure healthes.</p>
               <p>What ſeruice hath there beene, or may be ſo performed, which ſhall not be there lectured and read of a commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie drawne from the circumſtances, euerie parcell para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſed and altogither metamorphoſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Pill,</hi> as long as I haue liued, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places as I haue trauailed, I could neuer tell whither to go where I might heare a lecture of the art Military to be read before, but now I perceiue it is at your ordinaries where you vſe to dine and ſuppe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Now you know where experience is to bee ſought for, but from whom is it to be learned, what from your low countrey Souldiours onely do you thinke? no ſir, there is no ſuch matter, yet herhaps ſome of theſe readers haue been in <hi>France</hi> or in <hi>Flanders</hi> a fortnight or three weekes, but what is this in compariſon of their ſkill, or how ſhould they attaine to this grounded experience, that neuer ſaw an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie ſurpriſed in the field, and yet they will performe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conqueſts but ſitting at a table, then euer did <hi>Alexander</hi> when he conquered the world? you may eaſily thinke now this is not a monethes training in the fielde, that could thus inable theſe men, but that there is in them ſuch fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſcience and art, as doth tarre ſurmount their fielde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I thinke it be one of the ſeuen liberal ſciences that doth thus inable them, and I beleeue this excéeding ſkill conſiſteth eſpecially in the Art of <hi>Aſſe-trologie.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Your coniecture is pretie, and there is ſome ground to leade you vnto it, becauſe by <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> they may cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate both of fortunate and infortunate houres, and a cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:26442:22"/>of that ſkill may helpe himſelfe in all his enterpriſes, but for theſe men, they are not able onely to controule what is alreadie paſt, but they are of like abilitie to cenſure any thing that is yet to come, for let there be any enterpriſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, or ſeruice intended, and they will ſay aforehand what will be the ſucceſſe, as ſoone as euer they doe heare of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>It is wonderfull knowledge that you ſpeak of, and I thinke it euerie way comparable with the phiſition, that if he did but looke of a Cowes water, could tell how manie pintes of milke ſhe would giue in a yeare: and now I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that the firſt of your two eſpeciall meanes where mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall ſkil is to be ſought for, is at a <hi>London</hi> ordinarie: now me thinks your ſecond ſhould be in a Barbers ſhoppe, for there be many learned diſcourſes handled, or elſe I haue heard lies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>The ſecond meane whereby to attaine to the full perfection of Militarie ſkil, is by reading of bookes, <hi>Lucul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> by that onely ſtudie, became one of the nobleſt Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of all the Romanes: &amp; is it any maruaile, when there we may finde written a perfect forme, as well of orders, diſciplines, ſtratagems, and whatſoeuer hath béene obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, practiſed, and experimented by the moſt ſkilfull Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of all ages, and what knowledge our predeceſſors hath attained vnto by fortie yeares ſtudie, we may part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comprehend in one moneths reading.</p>
               <p>A man if he haue ſéene the accidents what hath happened in the warres thirtie or fortie yeares, it may be ſayd he hath ſéene much, but in bookes, what hath béene performed in a thouſand, may be ouerlooked in a verie few houres.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I will confeſſe where experience is holpen by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, there experience is farre more excellent, witte more pregnant and policie more readie, for without art who can conceiue the ordering and diſpoſing of men into ſeuerall formes of battaile, and ſodainely to alter them againe into new proportions, vpon new occaſions, or what memorie can containe ſo many formes, and ſo many proportions for
<pb facs="tcp:26442:23"/>all manner of numbers without Arithmetike: againe, for fortifications, who can comprehend any ſmall knowledge in it, or any ingenious inſtruments, that may be either apt for offence or defence, that hath not ſome ſkill in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ometrie?</p>
               <p>And as art and ſcience is thus beneficiall to Martiall knowledge, ſo the reading of bookes may be of like impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to giue giue vs light how warres haue béene arered, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, and performed, but he that hath no better experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then his reading, is as fitte to be a Captaine, and to haue the conducting of men to the fielde, as he that hath but read the art of Nauigatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be fit to conduct a ſhip to the ſea: for although <hi>Galene</hi> furniſheth the phiſition with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued medicines for euerie diſeaſe, yet he were a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate patient that in an extremitie of ſicknes would venture to take Phiſicke of him that hath neuer had better practiſe then his reading.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Thus I perceiue you will not admitte that a man may attaine to any perfection in Martiall ſkill, by reading or by the ſtudie of his booke, but he muſt néedes goe ſéeke it in the French or Low countrey ſeruices: and you do wel to arrogate to your ſelues this ſcience and knowledge, but there are ſome other that are of a contrarie opinion, who do thinke, that amongſt al the reſt that doe profeſſe armes, they muſt néedes be moſt inſufficient, that haue had their onely training but in thoſe tumultuarie and licentious warres, where neither order, diſcipline, nor any forme of <hi>tuo militia</hi> was euer obſerued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>But what wars are theſe that are ſo tumultuary and licentious as you ſpeake of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>The tumultuarie warres of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious warres of <hi>France,</hi> which haue beene firſt vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by ſedition, paſſion, and faction, and ſithence continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſpoyle, diſobedience, confuſion, and diſorder, where the precepts and preſcriptions of the great Captaines that haue ſerued in the well formed warres of Emperours and Kings, hath béene neglected, deſpiſed, and ſet at naught, by
<pb facs="tcp:26442:23"/>newfangled fellowes lately ſtart vp, with too much ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wéening of their owne experience, who vnder the pretence of ſkill haue confounded all ſkill left vnto vs by the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and in the ſteed thereof haue ſet vp a diſcipline of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious libertie, of ſpoyling, of robbing, of diſobedience, and diſorder.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I would not for forty ſhillings that any wiſe man in
<hi>England</hi> ſhould be of this opinion, or that any foole were ſo madde to beléeue it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>I can aſſure you it hath bin confidently perſwaded, by ſome that are not only knowne to be of a glorious wit, but alſo of no leſſe vnderſtanding in matters military, it is likewiſe receiued and beléeued, and by no ſooles, but by a great number of men of all ſortes, that do not only thinke thoſe wars to be licentious, tumultuary, diſordered, begun, maintained, and continued, againſt all right and honeſtie, but it is further beléeued amongſt them, that thoſe country ſeruices are vnfit to make a ſouldier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>But thoſe men that wil not beléeue that thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſeruices are fit to make a ſouldier, will eaſily beléeue that one of thoſe country prieſtes may make a god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>I know not that, but what is this to the purpoſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe if their beléefe be not méere madnes, it is a matter of more importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to make a ſouldier the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make a god, for they wil not denie but a prieſt may make a god but with thrée wordes ſpeaking, but they wil not confeſſe how thoſe wars will bréed a ſouldier in thirtie yeares training, it is no matter therefore what they affirme or denie in any thing, that are ſo blinde and ſenſleſſe in euery thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>But for al that captaine <hi>Skill,</hi> there be many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars inferred againſt your Low-countrie captaines, that are both odious and reproachful to be recited, and yet are ſo receiued, diſgeſted, &amp; belieued for matters of trueth, as wil not eaſily againe be diſſwaded to the contrary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>And may I craue to heare ſome of thoſe particulars what they be?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>I will not ſticke with you for that, but will recite
<pb facs="tcp:26442:24"/>ſome of them as I haue heard them aleadged, neither will I ſpeake of the low country ſeruices, how they haue béene managed in theſe latter times, but how they were abuſed, corrupted, and confounded, before my L. of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> came into that country, ſith which time, thoſe abuſes, corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and confuſions then hatched vp, haue bin retained vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til this day, and are yet preiudicial to the lawes, diſciplines, and ordinances left to vs by the great captaines of former ages, as in ſome particulars I will héereafter deliuer. But now a little of the ſeruices themſelues, and firſt to ſpeake of the inteſtine warres ſo many yéeres continued in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> where they haue not had any poſſible meanes to maintaine any other then a deformed and diſordered <hi>Militia,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the long continuance of thoſe troubls and diſſentions, whereby the rentes, reuenues, and other aydes and ſupplies of treaſure, haue ſo failed and wanted amongſt them, that they haue not bin able to pay their armies, whereby to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their men of warre in any diſcipline or order.</p>
               <p>The like again is to be ſaid of the Low countries, where both Mercenaries and ſubiects haue ſerued, but vnder a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular gouernment, conſiſting of diuers heades, where the hirelings of ſeuerall nations were drawne together, who through want of pay, (and hauing no other hope of reward for extraordinary deſert) liued only by forraging, filching, ſpoiling, and ſtealing.</p>
               <p>From hence it is not only to be preſuppoſed, but may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther certainly be concluded, that ſuch officers captaines and ſouldiers whoſoeuer, that haue had their training &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in ſuch licentious and tumultuary ſeruices (be they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects or mercenaries) are neuer fit after to ſerue in any refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med warres, who will not be reduced to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine themſelues vnder any ſeueritie of lawes martiall, where order or diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline ſhould be duly obſerued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>Theſe allegations (captaine <hi>Pill</hi>) that you haue here inferred with ſuch pregnancy and ſkill, we may well deride them into three parts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>You meane you may diuide them into thrée parts,
<pb facs="tcp:26442:24"/>I am ſure you will not deride nor ſcoffe at any thing that hath beene formerly auouched by men of great grauitie and wit: but let vs heare your diuiſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>Well, ſéeeing you will not haue it a deriſion, the ſumme of what you haue ſayde is thus much in effect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Firſt,</speaker>
               <p>the want of pay, inforceth the breach of diſcipline.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the breach of diſcipline inforceth but licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and tumultuarie warres.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, tumultuarie and licentious warres, traineth vp vnfitting Souldiours to be imployed in any reformed ſeruices.</p>
               <p>Nowe for the firſt, that the want of pay inforceth the breach of diſcipline, it is not to be denied, but in thoſe wars where Souldiours are not payde, or at the leaſt prouided for of victual, that they muſt neceſſarily make diſordered ſhifts, or famiſh: but doth the diſcipline of warre conſiſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that point, that when Souldiours be kept from ſpoile, that then thy be kept in true Martiall diſcipline? I trow in the French &amp; low cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey ſeruices they haue obſerued other parts of diſcipline, or they could neuer haue triumphed in ſo many worthie victories, againſt ſo mightie enemies.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond, ſay that the diſciplines of war were thus infringed and broken, doth this ſecond aſſertion (that the breach of diſcipline ingendreth but tumultuarie and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious warres) therefore neceſſarily follow? if that be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, what warres hath there euer beene performed, that may be ſaide to be legitimate, but that the diſciplines in ſome meane or other, hath béene infringed by diſordered perſons, or what gouernment vnder any Prince might not then bee detected and diſcredited, that hath his lawes and ordinances many times broken by diſordered ſubiects? and the church of God preſcribeth diſciplines, which are continually infringed and broken, but ſhall wee therefore when we haue occaſion to ſpeake of this church, put to any opprobrious or vnreuerend additions?</p>
               <p>Now who knoweth not but that the Low-country wars were firſt vndertaken for the rights and liberties of the
<pb facs="tcp:26442:25"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:25"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:26"/>Country, to frée themſelues from a tyranicall gouernment, vſurped by the Spaniards, as alſo for the frée paſſage of the Goſpel, and therefore both honeſt, iuſt, and godly? in like manner that of <hi>France,</hi> and therefore they cannot be ſayd to be tumultuarie, licentious, diſordered, &amp;c. becauſe their diſciplines are broken, but they worthily to be ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that will ſo maliciouſly report of them.</p>
               <p>Now for your third conſequence, that ſouldiours trained vp in thoſe ſeruices, ſhould be vnfit to be otherwiſe imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in any reformed warres: the concluſion is too ranke, it ſmelles from whence it came, but is it not poſſible, that a Souldiour, becauſe he hath béene driuen ſometimes for want of pay to reléeue himſelf from famiſhment, (although by the breatch of law) ſhall afterward reduce himſelfe, and be confirmable to any law, order, or diſcipliue, where hée ſhould either be better prouided for, or duly payed?</p>
               <p>I could alleage preſidents to make for my purpoſe, but what ſhould I néede? theſe colericke coniectures are well i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough knowne from whence they were firſt gathered, and by whome they haue ſithence béene retained: by thoſe that haue laboured at al times, and by all meanes, to diſgrace and deface the whole actions both of <hi>France</hi> and
<hi>Flanders,</hi> togither with the actours, becauſe they know we haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more fought in the defence of the Goſpell, in deſpight of their maſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>I muſt confeſſe, Captaine <hi>Skill,</hi> that for my ſelfe I neuer came in <hi>Flanders</hi> nor <hi>France,</hi> and therefore am able to deliuer nothing of mine owne knowledge, but what I haue heard by other mens reports, neither will I adde any thing of mine owne inuention maliciouſly to ſtander, I ſhal not néede to do that, for it is too much that is already publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and ſpread in the diſgrace of your French and Low-countrey Captaines, if al be true that is reported, but lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning generalities, I will ſpeake of ſome particulars. They are accuſed, not onely for deſpiſing, but alſo for peruerting the lawes, cuſtomes, orders and ordinaunces left vnto vs, by the great and notable Captaines of former ages inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uating,
<pb facs="tcp:26442:26"/>altering and inuerting al our ancient procéedings in matters millitarie by them preſcribed into orders of their owne inuention, attributing to themſelues greater ſcience and ſkill, then they will ſéeme to acknowledge in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, procuring moreouer (ſo much as in them lieth) by friuolous obiections and exceptions, taken againſt our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, to ſuppreſſe and extinguiſh the ſeruiceable vſe of our naturall Engliſh weapon, the long bow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>The matter is not great (Captaine <hi>Pil</hi>) whether theſe accuſations be of your owne making, or of any other mans reporting, for any great ſubſtance or witte that is in them, and for this particular, it were no great matter to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and confeſſe it to any man that would inforce it, for if it be a fault to innouate, I dare boldely auouch, there is no art, no ſcience, no occupation, no handicraft, nor any other profeſſion whatſoeuer, but they innouate, alter, and inuert, and that continually, and with great reaſon, when from age to age al things are perfected, bettered, and drawne to a forme of greater excellencie, then euer our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors vnderſtood of.</p>
               <p>The reaſon is, our anceſtors from time to time haue left vnto vs in writing, whatſoeuer they attained vnto by any manner of ſkill, knowledge, ſcience, or art, and we haue put vnto it our owne inuention, and what we can otherwiſe apprehend by dayly practiſe, I hope then that Souldiours are not generally ſo groſſe headed, when there is likewiſe left vnto them in writings, a perfect forme, as wel of orders, lawes and diſciplines, as of all other obſeruations, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hath béene practiſed by the moſt ſkilful Captaines of al ages, but that they could ſomething better their experience by twentie or thirtie yeares practiſe, in the French &amp; Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countrey warres, where ſo many honourable ſeruices haue béene ſo continually performed.</p>
               <p>Or why ſhoulde any man finde fault with ſouldiours, though they innouate their orders in theſe days, according to the practiſe and condition of the time? may it not be done without any preiudice to the grounds and principles left
<pb facs="tcp:26442:27"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:27"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:28"/>vs by the antiquitie. The phiſitions do fetch their directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from <hi>Galen, Hypocrates, Plinie, Paraſelſus,</hi> and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that haue left vnto them preſcriptions of phiſicke, and from whom our phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s at this preſent do fetch their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſt light, but if they ſhould now miniſter the ſelf ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines vſed in thoſe dayes by theſe learned Phiſitions, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt tenne patients if they recouered one, they would kill all the reſt.</p>
               <p>Shall we ſay now, becauſe our phiſitions do innouate, that they do therefore attribute to themſelues greater ſkill, learning, and ſcience then they would acknowledge in their predeceſſors.</p>
               <p>Now in martiall cauſes, although the antiquitie, who long before either Muſket or Caliuer were knowne, armed their people with croſbowes, targets, long ſwords, glaiues, partiſins, billes, and ſuch other, and according to thoſe ſorts of weapons, proportioned their battailes, in ſuch ſort as they might bring moſt handes to fight, which was good and neceſſarie for that time, when the ſeruice conſiſted altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by incounters of <hi>Pell Mell,</hi> and that they were ſtill brought to handie blowes, and had no other vſe but of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall weapons, but our ſquadrons being now armed with weapons of greater force, and more aduantage, haue left their auncient obſeruations to themſelues, &amp; haue follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an order perfected by time, and bettered by experience, when euerie Captaines page is not ignorant that the alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of weapon doth neceſſarilie inforce the alteration of order.</p>
               <p>For our naturall Engliſh weapon the long bowes, if there be a naturall that would perſwade better of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then men of experience doo finde ſeruice in them, I pray God ſende him more witte, and that is all the harme that I would wiſh him, and ſo we wil leaue them for the ſeruice in
<hi>Finburie fields,</hi> to the woonted Regiments of Prince <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Shordich.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pil</speaker>
               <p>Some other accuſations wherwith your Low coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try captaines are charged withall, is in the neglect and little
<pb facs="tcp:26442:28"/>care they vſed euen in vſuall and ordinarie cauſes, for it is not vnknowne to any man that hath iudgement in matters Military, but at the firſt forming of armies or regiments, there is likewiſe preſcribed lawes martial, the which are ſtil notified and made knowne, to the end, to containe their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in obedience, and that none might tranſgreſſe through ignorance: but this your low countrey captaines haue ſtill neglected, either vpon contempt, or by them not vnderſtood, which bewrayeth their malice or want of ſkil.</p>
               <p>The like neglect they vſed in the ſtabliſhing of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels at warres, and in the training and making ready of their ſouldiers in the practiſe of their weapons, in the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for them of powder, ſhot, munition, victualles, and all other neceſſaries, when they ſhould march vpon any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſeruice.</p>
               <p>Theſe, and many other like matters that are of common courſe and vſuall to ſouldiers that are of the leaſt ſkill and experience, were by them omitted and forgotten, or at the leaſt nothing at al reſpected.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I warrant you he that firſt ſmelt out theſe accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, had a tender noſe, but if he wanted not alittle wit, I am ſure he wanted a great deale of vnderſtanding, when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ſouldier, if he be but of one moneths training, is not ignorant, that where they erect armies, they forget not in like caſe to erect laws, the which at the firſt are vſually pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed with the ſound of a trumpet, and after hanged vp in the market places, either of their camps or garriſon towns, but theſe lawes and diſciplines are euermore preſcribed, by Generalles and Counſels of armies, and not by euerie par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular captaine or Colonel (and yet a Colonel may inſtitute for his owne priuate regiment) but not any lawes general, as your accuſation would intimate.</p>
               <p>Now the warres of the lowe countries were aſwel ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with Dutch, French, Wallons, Scottes, as Engliſh, which were al mercenary, and hirelings are euermore to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey lawes, and not to make lawes, but ſeruing vnder the prince of Orange and States, were likewiſe to receiue their
<pb facs="tcp:26442:29"/>lawes from whom they receiued their pay.</p>
               <p>But who was be of our Nation before my lord of
<hi>Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> time that had authoritie to preſcribe lawes, more then the French, Wallons, and Scottes? what, was it ſir <hi>Iohn Norris,</hi> that noble gentleman of our Nation that had béene there a Generall, but is now dead, and what can I ſay of him now he is dead, that ſhould not diminiſh the worth that was in him when he was aliue? what ſhal I praiſe his birth and honour of his race? the world knowes it was noble, but what is that in compariſon of his vertues? What then? his experience and knowledge in the field that aduanced ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny victories? if his friendes ſhould not applaude it, his foiled foes would yet confeſſe it: or ſhould I commend his noble and couragious heart, that no miſfortune could diſmay, nor enemies euer daunt, why <hi>Flanders, France, Portingale</hi> and
<hi>Spaine</hi> can witneſſe this, and his enemies may ſpight at it, but ſpeake againſt it they cannot? he is gone, but the honor he hath done to his countrey by his ſeruices wil not bée for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</p>
               <p>This noble gentleman, ſo highly renowned for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice amongſt the whole regiments, of Engliſh, of Dutch, of French, of Wallons and of Scottes, was eſpecially autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed and imployed as Generall: is there any man nowe ſo ſimple to beléeue that ſo great a captaine, reputed and well knowne to be ſufficiently able to direct an army againſt ſo great an enemy as the Spaniard, was not of like ſkill to ordaine and eſtabliſh lawes to containe his ſoulders in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</p>
               <p>For thoſe other neglects, for not eſtabliſhing a Counſell at warres, for not practiſing of ſouldiers, and not for proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for them munition, victualles, and other neceſſaries when they ſhould march, if theſe obiections were true, as they are moſt ſlaunderous and falſe, yet whom woulde you blame by theſe neglects but the Prince of Orange, and the States, the which if any man would take vpon him to doe, I thinke al the ſouldiors of <hi>Europe</hi> would hiſſe at him (as well enough they might) for who were ſo ſimple as to think
<pb facs="tcp:26442:29"/>that ſo famous a captaine as the prince of Orange, ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily renowmed for the managing of martial cauſes, were yet ſo careleſſe or ignorant, as not to preſcribe lawes, and likewiſe to prouide neceſſaries, as wel as to procure forces.</p>
               <p>Our Engliſh therfore are not to be charged with any one of theſe defects no more then were the Regiments of other Nations, namely the Dutch, the French, the Wallons, and Scots that ſerued with our Nation, al in one predicament, and receiued altogether their lawes from whom they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their pages: and theſe ignorant ill willers, that would ſpie out theſe faults, onely to depraue the Engliſh, are not much vnlike the olde ſeruant that ſometimes followes king <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, who vſed euermore to ſtrike him that ſtood next vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>There be ſome other obiectious againſt your Lowe country captaines for ſhameful miſdemeanors to their poore ſouldiers, ſome for ſending their companies into dangerous attempts, better hoping of their dead payes, then of any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice they could performe.</p>
               <p>Some other vpon hatred and diſpleaſure borne to theyr folowers, would deuiſe deſperate enterpriſes, of purpoſe to be reuenged.</p>
               <p>Others againe, when they had receined their ſouldiers pay, woulde likewiſe ſend them to the ſlaughter, that they might kéepe their payes in their owne purſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Me thinkes you ſhould tel me of ſome other of our captaines, that conſpired and practiſed with the Spaniard againſt the Prince and States that gaue them pay, and yet ſought to betray them in all their enterpriſes and ſeruices, and ſometimes would ſurrender vnto the enemies, townes and fortes which the Prince had committed to their guarde and placed them there in garriſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Skill,</hi> for theſe matters that I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready deliuered vnto you, and many other, that I haue yet to ſpeake of, all of them concerning the miſdemeanours of our captaines ſometimes toward their ſouldiers, ſomtimes towardes the country people that gaue them pay, and in
<pb facs="tcp:26442:30"/>whoſe defence they came to fight, and although that in this nature thus alledged, there be many ſhameful abuſes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they haue béene charged, yet to my remembraunce, I neuer heard of any mention made of treaſons, or traiterous ſurrendring vp of towns to the ſpaniards, as you haue now mentioned, I would be loath to do them ſo much wrong as to charge them with thoſe matters, that I neuer heard to be inforced againſt them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>And yet I can aſſure you, that theſe matters which you ſay you neuer heard of, were very true, and there were diuers of our Engliſh Nation that dealt moſt traiterouſly with the Prince, which did both conſpire and ſurrender vp townes to the enemy: and what is the matter that theſe collections of treaſon were not as well gathered in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of our Low country captaines, being true, as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which you haue heere inforced, being falſe, and ſome of them matters of impoſſibilitie, as thoſe very laſt obiections by you alledged (which euery ſouldiers boy could controule) as hereafter I wil make more euidently to appeare, euen to him that hath but halfe a ſence? But firſt of al let any man of vnderſtanding conſidder with himſelfe from whence theſe accuſations againſt our French and Low country captaine ſhould procéede, they are charged with many ſhameful abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the moſt of them vntrue, the reſt not worth the ſpeaking of, and for ſome other that were odious and hateful indéede, namely, treaſon, trechery, confederacie, and conſpiring with the Spaniard (and al of them apparant, and not to be gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) theſe matters were neuer ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of: nay theſe were no faults at al, but of my conſcience were rather eſtéemed to be workes of Supererrogation, meritorious matters, and as good a ladder to ſcale heauen withal, as a Bul of <hi>Scala coeli</hi> purchaſed from the Pope.</p>
               <p>Who ſeeth not now by whom theſe accuſations haue bin collected? it is wel enough to be perceiued, that they haue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their procéeding, but from olde papiſtical enmitie, that hath euermore béene buſied in defacing, diſgracing, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting thoſe French and Netherland ſeruices, and neuer
<pb facs="tcp:26442:30"/>ſparing to backebile thoſe that haue indeuoured themſelues in defence of the goſpel againſt their Pope: but the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part euermore faultleſſe though they performed nothing, but by treaſon, deceit, forgery, and al manner of villany.</p>
               <p>It is yet within the compaſſe of our owne memories, and hundreds of thouſands are now liuing that do well enough remember the very maidenhead of theſe wars, when they were firſt vndertaken, both in France and Flaunders, yea and in Scotland too, about matters of religion: howe long they were in armes and in ciuil broiles among themſelues, whileſt we liued here in <hi>England,</hi> by a moſt gratious go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement in the calme of quiet peace: we heard of warres round about vs, but with vs we had none but at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hall. Yet alarmes were ſometimes hote amongeſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, when their Ladies were diſpoſed alitle to be froward, our warlike inſtruments were laide aſide, and almoſt out of vſe, our ſhril trumpets for the field, were turned to ſtil mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke for the chamber, our drummes to tabrets, our martial exerciſes to maie games: this ſwéet and quiet peace brought with it a careleſſe ſecuritie, our gallant youths forgat to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtride the ſtirring ſtéedes, and walked vp and downe with feathered fannes in their hands, maſkes to couer their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and tawdry laces about their neckes, they became effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in al their demeanours, diſguiſing themſelues like demi-harlots. Our happines was enuied by our neighbors that did inuirone vs, but what could they doe to diſturb our quiet? it was the Lorde of Hoſtes that protected our
<hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth:</hi> and in the middeſt of this our delicacie when the wars were in their greateſt heat on euery ſide about vs, and their armies ſupplied by the moſt haughty hearts out of all the partes of
<hi>Europe,</hi> ſome of our Ingliſh blouds, no leſſe thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of honor, than he that is moſt couetous for pelfe, ſhaking off that nicity which the time had the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foſtered, thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into theſe ſeruices. Amongſt the reſt, our noble ſir <hi>Iohn Norris</hi> became a preſident to his countriemen, a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne for them to immitate, a lampe to giue them light, a loadſtarre to direct them in that courſe, that leadeth vnto ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:26442:31"/>and ſo to endleſſe fame: his example gaue hart &amp; corage to many others that folowed him, they ſerued in defence of the Goſpel, they attained by their ſeruice to that perfection of martial knowledge, that they are thereby inabled to ſerue their prince and country againſt all foes domeſticall or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine.</p>
               <p>Howe they bare themſelues in thoſe ſeruices againſt the pride of the Spaniardes, what honourable victories they obtained againſt the greateſt and moſt experimented Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines that chriſtendome could affoord, what ouerthrowes they gaue vnto them, and how many notable exployts they performed againſt them, the world I am ſure can witneſſe, and the matters are yet ſo freſh in memorie, that Spight may wel fret himſelfe to the gall, but to depriue them of their honour it can not, and therefore they are driuen to theſe threedbare ſhifts, to ſlaunder them with miſdemeanour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their ſouldiers, to accuſe them with the breach of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, the neglect of lawes, with ſuch a number of other trifles as would require a volume to expreſſe: and by this they would perſwade, that ſuch ſouldiers as had bin trained in ſuth licentious and tumultuary wars were neuer after to be imployed in any reformed ſeruices: and then if her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie ſhould haue any occaſion to vſe ſouldiers, where ſhould ſhe ſéeke for conducters that were of ſufficiencie? Diſgrace thoſe that haue hadde the practiſe and eſpeciall training in
<hi>Fraunce</hi> or <hi>Flaunders,</hi> and howe many are there left? or where ſhould we ſéeke for them, vnleſſe at your eightéen pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Academs, where you tell mee you haue ſuch reading of Martial Lectures?</p>
               <p>But I would not wiſh we ſhould hazard a dayes ſeruice to make tryall of the fortune and vnknowne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of theſe Academicall Captaines: for the others they haue béen ſufficiently tryed, and therefore are the better to be truſted. But notwithſtanding, theſe diſgraces that they would offer to our French and Low-countrey ſeruices, I cannot thinke that any Captaine, Gentleman, or ſouldiour whatſoeuer he be, that hath béene trained vp in thoſe ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:26442:31"/>(ſo maliciouſly reported on) do thinke the worſe of their owne ſkil or abilitie, becauſe enuie coupled with ignorance, hath ſought to diſable them: <hi>Dixit inſipiens</hi> cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may them, nor make them to thinke ſo euill of themſelues, but that they wil be alwayes readie to defend their credits, againſt any one that wil ſéeke to diſgrace them. Leauing other circumſtances, and to make a ſhort concluſion for all togither, I do not thinke how that honourable Earle (that is the glorie of this age for martiall matters) doth any whit at all miſlike his owne worthineſſe, becauſe he hath volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily oppoſed himſelf in thoſe French and Low-countries: but howſoeuer it pleaſeth him to thinke of himſelfe, lette vs acknowledge him to be as he is, his countries comfort, our <hi>Englands</hi> Champion, whom Honor &amp; Vertue haue ſtirred vp and pricked forward, but in the verie Aprill of his age, that he might become the guarde to his Prince, the refuge of his Countrey, and the bulwarke and caſtle of defence to them both. And now Captaine
<hi>Pill</hi> that it might appeare to any man of reaſonable iudgement, howe vnlikely thoſe accuſations are to be true which you haue hitherto allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, let vs but examine your thrée laſt obiections.</p>
               <p>Some Captaines (you ſay) would ſend their Souldiers into dangerous attempts, rather hoping after their dead payes, then expecting any ſeruice they could performe.</p>
               <p>Otherſome vppon diſpleaſure were ſent to the like en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes: and a third ſome, when they had receiued they: Souldiours payes, would ſend them to the ſlaughter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would keepe all in their owne purſes.</p>
               <p>What malicious reports be theſe? and yet not poſſible to be true, and I thinke (as I haue ſaide before) that euerie ſouldiers boy doth know it is death by the lawes of armes, for any Captaine to enterpriſe any attempt, without direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Generall or Councell at warres: perhappes ſome will ſay it is trueth, where the diſciplines of warres are truly obſerued, but the exceptions that are taken againſt thoſe countrey ſeruices, doth onely procéede vpon that neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, becauſe there was neither diſcipline nor order regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:
<pb facs="tcp:26442:32"/>but let vs therefore a little looke into their actions, and let any man that hath iudgement but conſider of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedings, it will appeare that a poore Prince aſſiſted with a few ſtates men, and ſhould continue wars ſo many yeares togither as they did againſt the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of Chriſtendome, for dominions, for money, for wealth, for expert and trained Souldiours, for great and notable Captaines and commanders raked together out of <hi>Spaine, Italy, Germany, Burgundie, Wallone, Albanie,</hi> yea, from all the parts of Europe, with the beſt Counſellers of warres, Inginers of all ſorts, and for all purpoſes, the beſt experimented that Chriſtendome could afford, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney procure, the which he conſumed there in large and huge ſummes (as the world can witneſſe) and yet two ſmal prouinces <hi>Holland</hi> and
<hi>Seland,</hi> a little corner heaped next the ſea, inuironed about with enemies on euerie ſide, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matched with numbers, what was it then that preſerued them but their verie order and diſcipline, the which if it had béene ſo neglected, that euerie man might haue deuiſed and attempted what himſelfe liſted, their warres would quickly haue had an end, and the King again poſſeſſed of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie? it cannot therefore be gaineſaid, but that next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, their greateſt defence was their order and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, preſcribed and ſette downe by the Prince of
<hi>Orange,</hi> (who was not to ſéeke in thoſe directions) and as by this I might well conclude, that they neither wanted diſcipline nor conduct, yet thus much I dare further anouch, and I do confidently affirme it of mine owne knowledge, that the breach of diſcipline in thoſe Low-countrey ſeruices, were euermore puniſhed with as great ſeueritie, as in any warres that hath béene vndertaken in our age, in what place or countrey ſoeuer.</p>
               <p>We may therefore conclude, that they wanted a great deale of matter, that were driuen to picke out ſo manifeſt vntruthes to ſlander thoſe actions, and as much as in them did lie, to diſgrace the actours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue Captaine <hi>Skill</hi> the firſt tale is neuer good,
<pb facs="tcp:26442:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>till the ſecond be heard: you haue verie reaſonably (in my opinion) diſcharged theſe accuſations, but yet thoſe that haue béene the firſt reporters of them, haue deliuered them for ſuch vndoubted truthes, and vnder the pretence of ſuch Martiall ſkil, that there be many thouſands in <hi>England</hi> that doe retaine them, and will hardly be diſſwaded to a contrary. And ſéeing I haue begunne to rip vp your abuſes, I will yet continue to tell you what I haue heard, ill fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red matters they be as they haue inforced the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt you, and therefore it would be much auaileable to your reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, if they could be ſufficiently excuſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>It is no great matter (Captaine <hi>Pill</hi>) what euerie Gooſecap doth conceiue in theſe matters againſt vs, he that would ſatiſfie all, ſhall ſatiſfie none: my deſire is onely to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie the wiſe, and for any thing that you haue hitherto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, I thinke a ſcoffe were more fit then an anſwere. But you ſay you haue more behind, you were beſt to empty your ſtomacke, for it is but draffe, and therefore out with al.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Your Low-country Captaines are accuſed for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too prodigal of their ſouldiours liues, for where it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore a cuſtome amongſt Captaines that are of ſkill or iudgement, vpon the aſſault of any place fortified, to make their approaches with trenches, croſſe trenches, gabions, and other inuentions as the ground will admit for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of their Souldiours liues, and neuer to make any attempt, vntill by batterie they haue made a ſufficient breach, and haue diſplaced the flankers, and other artilery of the enemies that might be noyſome or dangerous: but theſe deſpiſers of all diſcipline Militarie, haue béen ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of their Souldiours, that neglecting theſe principles, they haue ſent them as it were to the butcherie, to giue aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults to Caſtles, Sconces, and other ſuch fortifications, without either regard or conſideration of any of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes before ſpoken of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I warrant you captaine <hi>Pill</hi> he that comes in with all theſe trickes for the ſurpriſing of fortifications, hath heard much reading at your <hi>London</hi> Accadems, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue
<pb facs="tcp:26442:33"/>can better direct howe to aſſault the Caſtle in New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhſtréete, then to inſtruct them that haue had any continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the Low country ſeruices, which doth rather conſiſt in aſſaulting and defending fortifications, more then in any other incounters in the fielde, and therefore he that ſerueth there, is not to learne how to giue aſſaults.</p>
               <p>For the ſurpriſing of any Citie, Towne, Caſtle, Fort, Sconce, or whatſoeuer other place fortified, it is to be done by compoſition, by famine, by mining, or by aſſault.</p>
               <p>Compoſition is firſt imbraced by all good Captaines, for that is done without the ſpilling of bloud on either ſide.</p>
               <p>To winne by famine is vſed of policy, for the ſafetie of his people that doth beſiege, but many times inforced by conſtraint, when the ſcituation of the place admitteth of no other forcible meane.</p>
               <p>Mining is eſpecially preferred, as well for expedition, as the lightneſſe of the charge, if the ground will permit.</p>
               <p>Aſſault is the laſt refuge, and cannot be vſed vppon any plot that is well fortified without batterie, yet in ſome other places not throughly holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by nature, nor fully ſupplyed by Art are ſaultable inough with ladders and other prouiſion commonly vſed, before great Ordonance was inuented: and in the Low-countreyes wee had many earth workes, commonly called ſconces, ſome of greater, and ſome of leſſe importance, builded vſually vpon ſtreights or paſſages, and fortified accordingly as was behoouefull for the place: and where any one of them were found noyſome or preiudicial for ſeruice intended, there was likewiſe vſed ſuch force and meane for the taking of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in, as the ſcituation, or ſtrength or force of the place required: and I haue knowne diuers of thoſe Sconces haue béene taken by ſcale without any artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie, and yet without the loſſe of any one of the aſſailants: and what and if at ſome other time wee haue loſt men by aſſaults? it is not poſſible but if the defendants wil do their indeuour as they ought, that aſſailants can enter without ſome loſſe of men, no not when there is made breaches moſt eaſie to be aſſaulted, and therefore he that could finde this
<pb facs="tcp:26442:33"/>fault, I warrant you had good abilitie to find fault at any thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Your Captaines are yet once againe accuſed of flat coſonage towards their Souldiours, who to defeat them of their payes, gane them allowance of bread and chéeſe, and other victuall of the baſeſt ſort, which they call by the name of Prouand, a ſtrange name, and as ſtrange a deuiſe to coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin the poore men of their mony, &amp; in ſtéede thereof to giue them prouand, a matter neuer heard on before, as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by men of great experience, ſome of them yet liuing, that do wonder at the inuention, and doe very bitterly reprooue thoſe that were the firſt inuenters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>Is bread and chéeſe become ſo contemptible, that it is reputed amongſt the baſeſt kinde of victuall, O ſhamefull ſlaunder to <hi>Eſſex,</hi> where ſo many good Chéeſes are daily cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, and no leſſe indignitie to <hi>Wales,</hi> where a péece of ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted chéeſe is meate for a Monarch: but for thoſe that will accuſe our Captaines of coſinage towards their ſouldiours, becauſe they gaue allowance of Prouand, if there be but as much Martiall knowledge in any of them, as there is good meate but in the paring of an <hi>Eſſex</hi> chéeſe, I will be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be tryed by al the captains pages that euer haue but ſéene an army to march about any expedition, and if they ſhall finde mee guilty, I am contented to ſuffer the moſt vnhappie death that euer any man did yet indure, (and that I thinke were to be peckt to death with Capons.)</p>
               <p>The name of Prouand you ſay is ſtrange, and the deuiſe vſed by our Captaines no leſſe ſtrange, to coſin their ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours vnder the pretence of giuing them Prouand to kéepe away their payes. For my life they that doo ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the name, do thinke that the word Prouand was firſt deriued from an Oſterie, for there the Oſtler doth kéepe his prouender and giues it out againe from thence by meaſure, and many of theſe Oſtlers if they be not well lookt vnto, wil cooſin a mans horſe mightily in their Prouender, and this is the cauſe that they ſuſpect Captaines of the like cooſinage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Souldiours in their Prouand: and I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:26442:34"/>a fellow that once brought his maiſter a reckoning of riding charges, and amongſt many Items put downe in his bill, one was Item for a penieworth of horſe bread two pence. His maſter beganne to chafe at the reckoning, and deſired his man to make a better expoſition of that part of the text, the fellow making a low curteſie downe to the grounde, anſwered, forſooth ſir I dranke a pot of Beare whilſt my horſe was eating of his bread: now if there were any Captaine that vſed the like deceit, to drinke a canne of Reniſh wine whilſt his ſouldiours were eating of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uand, and after would put it downe vpon his Souldiours accounts, then here comes in the cooſinage, for otherwiſe, what commoditie for a Captaine to haue his Souldiours to be paide in prouand? if there bee any gaines to be made, it falles out to them that doe prouide and deliuer it, which is not the Captaine, and therefore to his himderance, for if he would make a profite of his companie, hee ſhould doe it much rather with receiuing of readie money, then in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of his ſouldiours payes in Prouand.</p>
               <p>And for thoſe that will affirme that the deliuering of Prouand was a matter neuer heard on before, but inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted onely by our Low-countrey Captaines, let them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend as much Martiall knowledge as they liſt, but I think they could not deuiſe to lay open their ignorance more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly, then not to know that Souldiours muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie be victualled vpon many occaſions, how well ſoeuer they be otherwiſe payed.</p>
               <p>One example that is familiar vnto vs I thinke may wel ſuffice: her maieſtie hath ſeruices in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in manie parts of that countrey, if ſhe ſhould pay her ſouldiours with ready mony, and not make prouiſion of victualles for them, where otherwiſe they can come by none, they might quickly famiſh with their mony in their purſes.</p>
               <p>This neceſſitie therefore hath euermore béene carefully prouided for, and the fault finders that vp think it ſo ſtrange a matter, that ſouldiours ſhould ſometime receiue their pay in victualles, no doubt their ſeruice hath béene in plentifull
<pb facs="tcp:26442:34"/>places, where they might either go to ordinaries, or ſend to the cookes for their dinner: yet I am not ignorant that vit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailers wil ſometimes follow a campe, but not at all times, nor yet in all places: and this Prouand that is here ſo much wondered at, was no other but as her maieſtie proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for her Garriſons in <hi>Barwick,</hi> and as all other Princes in Europe doe and haue done, whereſoeuer they haue held or do hold Garriſons of ſouldiours: and theſe prouiſions are not commonly made of Pheſants, Partrich, Quailes, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons and other like dainties, but vſually of Cheeſe, Butter, Bacon, Saltfiſh, and ſuch other victuall as ſhall néede no great cookerie, nor be long in making ready, eſpecially vpon any expedition of ſeruice.</p>
               <p>Thoſe therefore that would perſwade this victualling of Souldiours to be a matter neuer heard on before, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by our Low-countrie Captaines, for their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and commoditie, they haue herein ſhewed themſelues to be moſt ſimple and ignorant, and but in ordinarie matters appertaining to the warres.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Captaineſkill, if I ſhould proſecute theſe occaſions accordingly as I haue heard them inforced againſt your French and Low-country Captaines, I might yet inferre a hundred other obiections, and all of them verie bitter and diſgracefull vnto them: but I ſée your anſweres are ſuch as it rather falleth out to their diſgraces that were your accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, then by any meanes reproachfull vnto you that were accuſed: I will therefore omitte to ſpeake any further in theſe particular cauils, and will come to a matter of greater importance, being a general il, the which if it be true, as the reporter doth confidently proteſt, it may concerne no leſſe then our vtter wracke and ruine, and doth threaten in the ende the deſtruction of our Engliſh nation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Marie Captaine <hi>Pil,</hi> he that could ſpie me out that infirmitie, were worthie to haue a phiſitions fée, but he that could preſcribe a medicine for the maladie, were worthie to be eſtéemed the Aſcalaphus of his country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>The ſickneſſe is known, and the cauſe from whence
<pb facs="tcp:26442:35"/>procéeding is likewiſe gathered, by thoſe that are of great account for their experience and ſkill, it is found to proceede from a vehement hotte humour, abounding in your Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countrey captaines, who vnder the pretence of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of your weapons of fire (your Muſket and Caliuer) would thereby bring in carowſing and drunkenneſſe, to the aboliſhing and vtter ſubuerting of our artillerie, and the vſe of our long-bowes, the ancient and naturall weapon of our countrey, by the meanes whereof we haue tryumphed in many notable victories from time to time, and age to age, the which weapon if we ſhould now neglect, (as our Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countrey captaines doe altogither indeuour) this Noble Realme of
<hi>England</hi> ſo famed and renowned by the ſeruice of our artilerie, ſhould now be left to the ſpoyle, and remain but as a prey, fitte for euerie enemie that would attempt or aſſaile vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>Without doubt he that was the firſt finder out of this diſeaſe, had as great knowledge &amp; ſkill as the phiſition, who would needes perſwade his patient that he had taken a ſurfet by eating of a horſe, becauſe he ſaw a ſaddle lie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſickmans bedde. But in goodfellowſhippe captaine <hi>Pill,</hi> tell me true, is this an obiection againſt our Low-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie captaines, that vnder the pretence of the weapons of fire, they would bring in carowſing and drunkenneſſe, by meanes whereof (you ſay) they would ſuppreſſe the exerciſe of the long how, &amp; whereby our country ſhould he left a ſitte prey to euerie enemie that would attempt vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Skil,</hi> what I haue receiued, that I haue deliuered, I haue tolde you the true circumſtance of that I haue heard reported, if I haue failed in the manner, I am not miſtaken in the matter, if perhappes I haue ſomething miſſed of the words, yet I am ſure I haue not erred in the ſence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Why now I know what the reaſon is why cookes will neuer be without a Iacke of beere in the kitchin, and what is it that makes Smiths to bee ſo locall, that if you miſſe them at the forge, you ſhal be ſure to finde them in the
<pb facs="tcp:26442:35"/>alehouſe, they haue to deale with a thirſtie element, the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of fire, that brings in this carowſing &amp; drunkenneſſe, that againe expels the vſe of the long-bow, the neglect whereof threateneth <hi>Englands</hi> ouerthrow.</p>
               <p>So nowe howe theſe matters are depending the one of the other, tyed togither with a packthréed, and I will ſhew you a ſimilie how it may come to paſſe, an ancient collection to prooue by like circumſtance that drinking may bring a man to heauen: and thus ſayth the text: <hi>He that drinkes well, ſleepes well, He that ſleepes well thinkes no harme. He that thinkes no harme ſinneth not, and he that ſinneth not goes to heauen:</hi> here is now the concluſion, and he that can choppe me vp ſuch Logicke, I hope may beare the bell for a Logician: let him go where he liſt.</p>
               <p>Now for your water-caſting wiſards, that in the déep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their experience (as you ſay) haue looked into
<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> eſtate, and do think that the neglect of the long bowe may bréed ſuch a ſurfet as you ſpeake of. God be thanked the ſickneſſe is nothing ſo dangerous, as the ſilly ignorant ſort would perſwade it, the nature of the diſeaſe hath bin exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and carefully conſidered of by men that are no leſſe renowned for their wiſedme &amp; experience, then honored for the loue &amp; zeale they beare to their country, they haue found the firſt to be a matter of no importance, but rather thought it behooueful and neceſſary for vs to inure our ſelues to that diet, which all the nations of the worlde beſides do eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally account of, and haue retained as a reſtoratiue to their better ſafty, which being by vs neglected, might be ſuch a preparatiue for an enemie to take aduantage by, as your Phyſitians could neuer be able to reſtore, not with all the medicins they could compound, eyther of their croſſebows or long bowes.</p>
               <p>A foole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crach him then ſay I that would giue vs ſuch pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, or vnder the pretence of a Cullis whereby to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs, would giue vs indéede a potion that would vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly poyſon vs.</p>
               <p>What ſhould I ſay more then to theſe calculating com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions,
<pb facs="tcp:26442:36"/>that are ſo narrow eied to look into commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth cauſes, that they thinke the countries good is euermore neglected, where their owne fooliſh preſcriptions are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes obſerued.</p>
               <p>Let ſuch vaine prognoſticators fable what they liſt, God hath bleſſed <hi>England,</hi> he hath plentifully poured his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings vpon vs: firſt, in our moſt gratious <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whom he hath eſtabliſhed, and holden vp in deſpighte of all Popiſh practiſes, he hath deliuered her when ſhe hath béene compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with many dangers, whereby he hath ſhewed his mercy to vs her people, whome ſhe hath ſtill gouerned in happy peace and proſperitie. He hath giuen her the aſſiſtance of a moſt graue and diſcréet counſell, amongſt the reſt <hi>Burghley</hi> by name, the man admired through chriſtendome, whoſe watchful eies to preuent inſuing miſchiefes, haue euermore béene vigilant, whoſe wiſedome next vnder God and her Maieſtie hath béene the beſt conſeruer of our quiet, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py peace, whoſe experience in commonwealth cauſes, is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular to himſelfe. And for the action of warre. O noble erle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> how is <hi>England</hi> bleſſed in thée? thou haſt honoured thy country with thy victories obtained, enriched it with the ſpoiles of thine enemies, fréeed it from the force of foes that were ready to aſſaile it, whom thou haſt diſmayed and daunted at their owne doores.</p>
               <p>If I ſhould now ſpeake of domeſticall matters, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of lawe and iuſtice here at home, according to equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, right, and conſcience, <hi>England</hi> may think it ſelfe happy, and the Court of Chauncery hath as great cauſe to glorie, where <hi>Egerton</hi> adorneth the bench.</p>
               <p>Thus you may perceiue (captaine <hi>Pill</hi>) that
<hi>England</hi> is in no ſuch diſtreſſe as your dreaming dizardes woulde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, they threaten vs to be almoſt at deaths doore, when there is no manner of ſigne nor ſhew of ſicknes, you ſée who they be, captain <hi>Pil,</hi> that are <hi>Englands</hi> watchmen, and haue ſo conſecrated themſelues to the good of the commonwealth, that what perills may paſſe which ſhall not be by them diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and what forraine practiſes or domeſticall diſorders
<pb facs="tcp:26442:36"/>can be ſo plotted out, which ſhall not be by them both fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéene and preuented, if it do either concerne the good or ill of our country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Skil,</hi> me thinkes you haue béene too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious and briefe in the ſubiect that you haue now vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, a breath of winde is not enough to comprehend their praiſes, that would aſke a longer diſcourſe than al that hath bin hitherto debated betwéene vs: but will not your words be taken in ill part? for there be many honourable perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in <hi>England,</hi> that without doubt are faithful and firme both to their princes and countrey, that perhaps wil hang the lip, and thinke themſelues to be greatly wronged, that any one ſhould be ſo particularly preferred before them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially for thoſe cauſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I hope the praiſe of one is no diſpraiſe to another, neyther am I ignorant, but am vndoubtedly perſwaded, that there be many, as well of the nobilitie, as other of the inferiour ſort and calling, that are of equall deſire, though not of equall abilitie: I commend him that can follow the wiſe aduiſe of others, but I preferre him that can foreſée pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils that are to come, and is able to diſcerne of things néede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and requiſite. My concluſion is, I honour all that are worthy of honour, but I ſay againe (and without offence to any I hope I may boldly auouch it) theſe that I haue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med are the ornaments of
<hi>England,</hi> the Miniſters of God next vnder her Maieſtie, by whom
<hi>England</hi> is made happy, the one famous for his counſell, the ſecond renowned for his magnanimitie, the third reuerenced for his iuſtice, and al of them honored for the care they haue of their countries good, thrée notable pillers of our commonwealth, to whom I may adde a fourth, the noble Lord of <hi>Hunſdon,</hi> who for his fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to his prince, matched with equall loue to his country, together with the magnificence and nobleneſſe of his mind, may march in equall ranke with thoſe that are moſt highly honoured, and for their vertue moſt worthily renowned.</p>
               <p>You ſée now (captaine <hi>Pill</hi>) that
<hi>England</hi> is not ſo negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently prouided too, that it ſhould runne into ſuch vnexper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:26442:37"/>danger as your ſquint eyed Diuiners would pretend to foreſee, but let them dreame and make what doubtes they liſt, they are to be ſuſpected of ſome defects that doe ſeeme to be ſo feareful of the moone-ſhine in the water.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>But captaine <hi>Skil,</hi> you deale ſomewhat too roundly in this matter, I woulde wiſhe that you coulde more adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly conſider of my ſpeeches, the matter obiected is againſt your Low country Captains, who vnder the pretence of the excellency of the weapons of fire, would bring in carowſing and drunkenneſſe, and thereby would vtterly ſuppreſſe and aboliſh, our longbowes, &amp; archery of <hi>England.</hi> From hence iſſueth this danger to our countrey, that being bereaued of this weapon which our predeceſſors haue euer found ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable, and of ſo great aduantage againſt their enemies, we ſhould thereby ſo weaken and diſable our ſelues, againſt any that would inuade vs, that we ſhould rather be left to the ſpoile, than be able to make defence: and although that thoſe noble patrons of our country which you haue named, are ſufficiently able to diſcerne of perils (as I doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their vertue to be farre excéeding the commendation you haue deliuered, ſo there is no doubt but that they in their wiſedomes can well enough conſider how this neglect of ours may threaten greater daunger and turne to a worſe conſequence than you do conceiue of, when it is auouched by them of knowne experience, and the reaſons fortified by many preſidents of great antiquitie drawne from
<hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in
<hi>Greece,</hi> and from many other countries and kingdomes: beſides, it is prooued by many examples, what notable conqueſts, haue béene ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the vſe of bowes, and how many nations, king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and common wealths haue béene ſubuerted, ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and brought into ſeruitude, where they haue neglected that notable weapon, and ſet it aſide.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>If our Low country Captaines do pretend ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie in the weapons of fire, they do it by good authoritie, hauing had ſufficient triall of the effects, but how theſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons ſhould bring that carowſing and drunkenneſſe you do
<pb facs="tcp:26442:37"/>ſpeake of, I proteſt it paſſeth my conceit howe it may hang together.</p>
               <p>For drunkenneſſe I do pronounce it to be a moſt deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vice, beaſtly and hateful in the opinion of any man, that is worthy the reputation of a man, and I haue knowne ſom of our Low countrey Captaines, that haue béene ſhameleſſe when they were drunke, but they haue bluſhed again when they were ſober, but he that delighteth in that vice, is a fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter companion for ſwine, then worthy to aſſociate men.</p>
               <p>And is it our Low country captaines that haue brought in the exerciſe of carowſing and drunkenneſſe, I wonder at them that could trauel ſo farre countries, to fetch ſo many preſidents, for the antiquitie of bowes, and could not haue brought one preſident with them, for the antiquitie of drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, if it were but how <hi>Alexander</hi> killed his <hi>Clytus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for carowſing it was new chriſtned in <hi>England</hi> from a carowſe to a hearty draught, I thinke before the moſt of our Low country Captaines were borne.</p>
               <p>Now for this neglect of the long bow which is thought to be a matter of ſuch danger, and ſuch a weakening to our country, we may commende them a litle for their care that do ſo feare it, but neuer a whit for their experience that would perſwade it, and leaſt of all for their wit that would beléeue it. For the preſidentes that haue bin ſo tranſported from thoſe far countries in the behalfe of the long bow, they are all as patte for the purpoſe (that ſhould be prooued by them) as he that alleaged that <hi>Tenterden ſteeple</hi> was the cauſe of <hi>Goodwin ſandes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>If you will denie preſidents becauſe they are farre fetcht, that do make good in the behalfe of the bowe, we wil bring you ſome néerer home, and I hope you will not denie our own hiſtories &amp; chronicles, that do concerne our owne actions, ſome of them within the compaſſe of mens memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries yet liuing, how many teſtimonies are there recorded in the behalf of our archery, what ſeruices they haue performd what conqueſts they haue atchieued, &amp; what victories they haue obtained, I ſhal not néed to relate them in particular;
<pb facs="tcp:26442:38"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:38"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:39"/>they are ſo apparant to euery reader, that I hope you will not doe your ſelfe that wrong to gainſay them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>And with what diſcretion can you or any one for you alleadge them? you bring vs out preſidents, what ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces haue béene perfourmed by our archery in times paſt, but where was then that celleritie and readines in the weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of fire that is now practiſed? you tell me of conqueſts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed, and victories obtained, but it was <hi>in diebus illis,</hi> when neither muſket nor caliuer were knowen nor heard of.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe the bow hath béene a weapon of great effect in ſeruice, but the caſe is altered, euery thing hath his time, and I could wiſh with all my heart, that our archery of <hi>England</hi> were but by the one halfe ſo effectuall, as ignorant men will dreame of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>That the bow is more effectuall then you do eſtéem it, is to be prooued by ſuch forcible reaſons, as your low co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try captaines are not able to reſiſt, let vs but ſéeke the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the holy ſcriptures, and wée ſhall finde what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the prophet
<hi>Dauid</hi> made of that weapon after the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow &amp; death of king
<hi>Saul,</hi> beſids in one of his Pſalmes he calleth them, A mightie power, and in another place, The veſſels of death.</p>
               <p>Another of the prophets ſent from the almightie to terrefie the people for their ſinnes, ſpeakng in the perſon of GOD ſaith, That he had bent his bow, and made ready his qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Many other places might be inferred to confirme the fury and force of that weapon, if men were not ouermuch giuen to infidelitie and miſbelèefe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>If the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> had ſlaine <hi>Goliath</hi> with an arrow out of a bow, as he kilde him with a ſtone out of a ſling, I perceiue there would haue bin ſome great hold ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the matter, for the credit of bowes, but if he had kild him with a bow, muſt it therefore be granted that bowes did excell all other weapons? <hi>Sampſon</hi> kilde a great number of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> with the iawe-bone of an Aſſe, yet if I ſhould fight I would not truſt to that weapon, if I might
<pb facs="tcp:26442:39"/>haue mine owne choice.</p>
               <p>And becauſe it is ſaid by the prophet, that he had bent his bow, doth that therefore conclude the bow to be moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of all other weapons? This logicke is much like vnto his, that affirmed men to be more godly then women, his reaſon was, becauſe there is a towne in <hi>Surty</hi> that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Godlime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> but there is neuer a town in <hi>England</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Godlywomen, ergo</hi> men are more godly then women. And becauſe God hath ſaid, I haue bent my bow, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer makes mention that he had chargde his muſket, <hi>Ergo</hi> the bow is better then the muſket. And I remember ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place where it is written, He had whetted his ſworde, but it is not ſaid that he had made ſharpe his browne bill, &amp; therefore the ſword is a better weapon then a browne bill: But captaine <hi>Pill,</hi> let vs leaue this logicke, for it is twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to one if euer it be knowne, the ſchole boyes wil laugh at vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill.</speaker>
               <p>Let them laugh (captaine <hi>Skill</hi>) at your errour that do attribute ſuch commendations to your muſket and cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that thereby you would condemne and ſuppreſſe all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weapons of farre greater excellencie and vſe, but if you will néeds giue ſuch principalitie to your weapons of fire, it is neither your muſket nor caliuer that are ſo ſingular, but as it is reſolued by captains of great ſkill and knowledge, the harquebuz is to be preferred before them both, and that for many conſiderations by them alleaged.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>And what might be the conſiderations that your great captaines haue ſo preferred the harquebuz?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>For that the Harquebuz is more maniable in a ſkirmiſh, and a great deale more light to make a haſtie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trait, where your Muſketiers in ſuch actions through the weight of their péeces, are driuen to throw them quite away and to truſt altogether to their héeles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Then I perceiue the errour of our Low-country captaines is, becauſe they would arme their people in ſuch ſort as they might be able to put the enemie to a retrait, but your great captaines cleane contrary would haue them
<pb facs="tcp:26442:40"/>ſo appointed as they might be light and nimble to runne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way themſelues: and he that ſhould bring his men but fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with paltry harquebuz to incounter the muſket and caliuer were fitter indeede to runne away from an ennemie that would offer to aſſaile him, than be able to tarry by him in the field.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>And al the reaſon you can make, is, becauſe of the farre ſhooting, and it is not denyed, but that your muſket wel charged with good powder, would carry a ful bullet 24. or 30. ſcores: but yet that any of them ſhould giue their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies aboue tenne, twenty, or thirty peeces at the vttermoſt, is accounted but a méere mockerie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>And if the farre ſhooting be of no aduantage, whie then there is no oddes betwéene a bodkin and a pike, but in truth one of the moſt eſpeciall cauſes that muſkets are ſo much regarded, is becauſe they may be brought 24. and 30. ſcores off to beate vpon ſquadrons either of horſmen or foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to breake and diſmember them: and in like maner to beate paſſages or groundes of aduantage taken by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or for many other ſeruices, either aſſailing or defending as wel in the field, towne, trench, or where, or howſoeuer, the muſket is ſtill found to be a weapon of wonderfull ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, and onely by the farre ſhooting: but for thoſe that do no better valew of the muſket, but to giue their volies at tenne, twenty, or thirtie paces: it ſhould ſéeme they knew of no other ſeruice in the field, but when enemies do meet, they will ſtrait drawe their ſquadrons to an encounter, which ſheweth their little vnderſtanding, for when ſuch méetings do happen, captains that be of experience are accuſtomed to place the ſtand of pikes (wherein conſiſteth their ſtrength) vpon ſome ground of aduantage, and as néere as they can will bring ſome hedge, ſome ditch, ſome ſhrubbes or buſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or ſome other like helpes, betwéene them and the enemy, becauſe they would not lie open to the muſket ſhot, that the other will then thruſt out, (if they can be ſuffered) to play vpon theſe ſquadrons or armed men 24. and 30. ſcores off. Loole ſhot being thus ſhaken off, oportunities and aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:26442:40"/>are watched on both ſides, as well by horſemen as foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to take their times and occaſions, their ſquadrons ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtil a good diſtance the one from the other, with wings, fillets, and troupes of ſhot, to giue thoſe volies at hand (that you ſpeake of) if they ſhould be charged, and many times it falleth out, that ſquadrons be broken and put to a retrait, by aduantages taken and procured by theſe ſkirmiſhes, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially being galled and beaten by the furie of ſhot a farre off, when the ſquadron of the contrary part hath not ſo much as appéered in ſight: thoſe weapons therefore are moſt to bée valewed that wil do his execution fartheſt off, and if it were poſſible to deuiſe a weapon that would annoy and ſpoyle an enemie in diſtance as farre as thrée muſkets, ſuch a weapon were thrée times more auaileable for ſeruices at longth, and tenne times more profitable for ſuch exploites, then once to giue volies ſo néere at hand, to be deliuered within that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of tenne, twentie, or thirtie paces as you ſpeake of.</p>
               <p>And yet for thoſe ſeruices when occaſion ſhall require, what weapon more terrible than the muſket, that within twentie, thirtie, fortie, or a hundred paces, will deliuer foure or fiue caliuer ſhot at one diſcharge, to the wonderful ſpoile of ſuch as wil approch them: and for this occaſion the fillets and wings of battelles and ſquadrons, are compounded of thoſe weapons to giue their volies if they ſhuld be charged: and this is the cauſe that the Spaniard finding this wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon to be of ſo great importance for all manner of ſeruices, hath conuerted the greateſt part of his ſhot into muſketires: and this is the cauſe that ſuch of our Nation as haue ſerued againſt them, may the better ſpeake of that weapon by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience what themſelues haue found.</p>
               <p>For others that haue but gathered their preſidents from tabling houſes or otherordinaries, may better ſpeake accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their knowledge then according to the matter. And who be thoſe that wil euermore contend againſt that wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, but ſuch as haue not ſéene their effect and ſeruice in the field, but inforceth againſt them their hundred yéere olde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampls, before ſhot was euer perfited, or in maner knowne.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26442:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26442:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:26442:42"/>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Thus I do ſée we Engliſh men are very ſharp wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to make reaſons againſt our ſelues, and Lord how rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy we be to change a certaintie for an vncertainty. But wil you ſo diſable our bowes, that you wil allow them no place in the field? I hope againſt horſemen you wil do them ſome fauour, for to ſpoile and gall horſes, what weapon of more effect, or who wil deny them that right?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>But how ſhal wee bring them to that place of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice where they may do this annoyance to horſemen? it is not to be deuied but that Archers would performe great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice againſt horſemenne: if they might be brought to the place where they might ſerue, but as they muſt be fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, either with hedge, ditch, or other artificiall meanes that horſemen may not charge them, ſo the place from whence they may do their execution, muſt be open and plaine, where whileſt they drawe their bowes, their bodies muſt remaine in open view. Now what enemie of iudgement would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to kéepe ſuch a ground, but that with thrée or foure hundred muſketiers they would diſplace two thouſand Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and without any manner of danger to themſelues, by reaſon of their farre ſhooting, ſo that he might be counted a very weake witted enimy that would ſuffer vs to bring our bowes where they might performe any exploit either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt horſemen or footemen, but contrariwiſe for the muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket and the caliuer euery hedge, euery ditch, and euery thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, which almoſt euery ground affordeth, is ſuch an aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for them, that they wil not be diſplaced, but with great daunger and loſſe of the aſſailants, where they haue once planted and ſetled themſelues.</p>
               <p>Againe, they can ſerue out of euery buſh, and from behind euery trée vndiſcerned or ſéen by thoſe that ſhal ſerue againſt them, whereas the Archer muſt ſtand in open ſhew, and make himſelfe an open marke to his enemie, or otherwiſe he cannot ſerue at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Why then belike all the aduantage that your ſhot hath, is to hide themſelues. But let me aſke you a queſtion: if a thouſand of your ſhot, and a thouſand of well choſen Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<pb facs="tcp:26442:42"/>were togither in the plaine fielde; which part would you there take if you might haue your owne choyſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>But in what field doe you meane (Captaine <hi>Pill</hi>) let me firſt know that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>And what a queſtion is that to be aſked, if it be in a field where there is no aduantage of couert for your ſhot to hide themſelues in, I take no other exceptions to anie field.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Mary ſir but I doe, and your queſtion may be full of ſubtiltie, for I remember there was one that ſhould haue béene begged for an Ideot, and ſuch a queſtion was aſked of him, how many legges a ſhéepe had, he aſked againe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they meant a ſheepe as he went to the butchers, or as he came from the butchers? why, what difference make you in that (ſayd the demaunder?) great difference ſir (anſwered the other) for a ſhéep going to the butchers hath foure legs, but comming from the butchers, hath but two legges and two ſhoulders. And your queſtion may haue the like fallace, for you aſke me if a thouſand ſhot and a thouſand Archers were in the fielde, whoſe part I would take, nowe if you meane in <hi>Finsburie field,</hi> as they are there with the Duke of <hi>Shordich,</hi> and Prince <hi>Arthur,</hi> I would then take part with the Archers, for then I were ſure I ſhould neuer catch harme with a bullet, and I ſhould haue good chéere, during the time of our ſeruice: but if it were in the field where they ſhould ſerue for their liues the one againſt the other, if I ſhould then ſay I would take part with the Archers, I am afraid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Captaine <hi>Pill,</hi> that you would begge mée for an Ideot.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>And I doo knowe them againe that do thinke their experience as good as yours, or as any that ſhall ſay to the contrarie, that dare vndertake with one thouſand of choyſe Archers, to incounter with two thouſand of the beſt ſhotte you can bring into the field.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I would ſome of thoſe vndertakers would vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to build vp Poules ſteeple, for me thinks they ſhould aduenture to vndertake any thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:26442:43"/>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>they dare aduenture to vndertake this, and ſo to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfite your ſhotte, that they ſhall not dare to ſhewe theyr faces in the field, or elſe they will looſe their liues, or wil wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for the performance al that euer they haue in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Nay if they go to wagering, I on the contrary part will play them faire play, for I wil lay them Cockpit-ods that they ſhall not do it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Sir I dare vndertake you ſhall be taken vppe, but what is that you call Cockpit-oddes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>Cockpit-oddes is lightly two to one, and he that wil vndertake to make good your challenge, I will lay both my pantofles to his wit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>It ſhould ſéeme Captaine <hi>Skill</hi>) you are driuen to a bare boord, that are faine to ſhift out your matters with ſuch vnſauorie ieſts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I hope they ſmell as ſwéete as the challenges you do make, of one thouſand Archers againſt two thouſand of our beſt ſhotte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pil</speaker>
               <p>I tell you againe, there be thouſands of that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and do thinke that an Archer hand to hand, is by great oddes too hard for any ſhotte you are able to turne againſt him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>I tell you againe they are in a wrong opinion, and I account him a verie inſufficient ſhot that dare not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take any Archer that euer I heard on; vnleſſe it be one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>It is happie you will confeſſe one Archer of ſuch ſufficiencie, but I pray you who may that one Archer be that you ſtand ſo much in doubt of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Marie ſir it is <hi>Cupid,</hi> he that neuer ſhootes but he doth ſome miſchiefe (they ſay) and therefore there is no dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with him, and I would neuer wiſh my friends to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue theſe ieſts will neuer be left off, but they are your beſt helpes, and therefore to be borne withall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>I muſt commend you (Captaine <hi>Pill</hi>) for your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, but you are deceiued, I vſe no ſuth helpes for want of matter, but I haue learned that friuolous queſtions are
<pb facs="tcp:26442:43"/>fitteſt to be anſwered with a ieſt, or not to be anſwered at all, and thoſe compariſons that you haue made of your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers with our Muſket and caliuer, are ſo farre from al rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and iudgement, that they are to be laughed at by anie man that hath either reaſon or iudgement, or any maner of ſparke of experience in him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pil</speaker>
               <p>If this be inough that becauſe captaine <hi>Skill</hi> hath thus affirmed, therefore it is true, there ſhal néede no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwere, but if you wil truely diſcerne of theſe doubts, let vs examine what may be the defects as wel of your wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of fire, as of our archers, or what caſualties may fall out that may hinder their ſeruices: by this you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue which weapon is of greateſt effect, and likelieſt to do ſeruice.</p>
               <p>Then firſt for your Caliuer and Muſket: there be manie accidents that may happen through the default of ſuch ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours as ſhall vſe them, for beſides they may neglect to kéepe their péeces in ſeruiceable ſort, ſo in the very inſtant of their ſeruice they may faile in their ſight, as commonly with too much haſte they are accuſtomed to do, whereby they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhoote greatly to indanger: againe their bullets being too low, may flie vncertain, in continuance their péeces may waxe hot, there may be fault in their pouder, there may bee fault in their match, there may bee fault in their charging, there may be many other faults and caſualties, that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to ſhotte, and all of them an impeachment to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: but for Archers, what is there more then the breaking of the bow, or the breaking of the ſtring, that may be anie impediment to them? and this is a verie ſeldome caſualtie, and may be preuented with a matter of nothing, for a little waxe, roſine, and tallow tempered ouer a fire, and chafed in with a wollen cloth, preſerueth the bow: &amp; for the ſtring, if it be made of good hempe, water, glew, and ſtrongly whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with ſilke or fine thréed, it will not faile in a long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance: the Archer therefore being leaſt ſubiect to miſchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is of greateſt importance, and readineſſe for ſeruice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>But captaine <hi>Pill,</hi> this argues you to be a very
<pb facs="tcp:26442:44"/>partial phiſitian, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wold not likewiſe find out ſome medicins for ſhot whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue found ſo many infirmities depending vppon them, but haue left them to all their diſeaſes, as though they were incurable: but if I would deale as nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly with your archers, as you haue done with our ſhot, I could pick out more caſualties then the breaking of a bow or a bow ſtring, for it might be they might loſe their ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting gloues, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they could not ſhoot for hurting of their fingers. Againe, they might haue ſore elbowes, and then they could not draw their bowes: but eſpecially they are to take héed whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhoot, that they ſhoot not the fethered end of their arrows forwards, for then they wil neuer flée right.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pil</speaker>
               <p>What gawds be theſe you do ſtil adict your ſelf vnto? ywis it would be more for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> credit of your cauſe, to anſwer with more diſcretion, theſe frumps are to little purpoſe, but rather to the diſcredit of that you would faineſt maintaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Pil,</hi> I do deale more diſcréetly with you then I perceiue you can conceiue of: for you know it is faire play in euery tennis court to toſſe you backe againe your owne balles, that your ſelfe haue firſt ſerued to the houſe: and becauſe you ſpeake of gaudes, what gaudes be theſe that you haue inferred againſt ſhot? that they may neglect their ſightes, that their bullets may be too low, that there may be fault in their pouder, that there may be fault in their match, that there may be fault in their charging: what obiections be theſe but gaudes and trifles? for who would allowe him for a ſhot, that taketh no ſight of his marke but ſhooteth at randon, or that careth not whether his pouder be wet or dry, or that will not kéepe his péece in ſeruiceable ſort from ruſting or furring, or that knowes not how to giue his péece her due charge, but will put in the bullet before the pouder, or that thinketh his peece neuer to be charged till hee hath filled the barrell to the very toppe? I haue knowne ſuch, but what of this? are theſe things to be reckoned in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement of perfect ſhot? no they are but cauils, and the queſtion is not of the imbicilitie of the man, but of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and aduantage of the weapon being vſed in his kinde,
<pb facs="tcp:26442:44"/>and according to ſkill: But for theſe accidents before ſpoken of, if any of them happen, the fault is not to be imputed to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to the ſouldier that hath committed ſome negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. Confeſſe now a truth, &amp; ſay that the muſket &amp; caliuer are of greater force &amp; ſeruice in the field or elſewhere, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſhot that hath bin hitherto knowen, if the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that beareth them be expert, as he ſhuld be, and neglecteth no part of his dutie, and then I will anſwere you thus.</p>
               <p>The very meane to bring a ſhot to perfection and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, is practiſe, and then that man is much to blame, that (ignorantly and without knowledge) wil ſéeke to diſſwade that which doth ſo greatly concerne his countries good, and would aduiſe vs to neglect a weapon of ſuch excellencie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted (&amp; trie to be of) in all the partes of Chriſtendome, that would ſo weaken vs, &amp; aduantage any enemie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would aſſaile vs, as God defend that by any perſwaſion we ſhould be induced to ſubmit vnto, but rather with all carefulnes to inure them, knowing that the very perfection of thoſe we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, doth eſpecially conſiſt in the practiſe of the bearer, and he which hath not celeritie and redines to vſe them, is liker to end anger a friend, then hurt an enemie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>And for this celeritie and readines the archer is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to be preferred, that are alwaies ready to giue their volies, and to ſhoot foure or fiue arrowes, before your ſhot ſhall be able to diſcharge one bullet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>This poſition is one of the greateſt reaſons that they haue in the behalfe of archers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they will ſhoote faſter &amp; oftener then ſhot can do, but this is euer more aleaged by ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant men, for although it be true that euery archer ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily will ſhoot faſter then euery ſhot can do hand to hand, yet for ſeruice to be performed in the fielde, if there be 1000 ſhot, and 1000 archers, euery captain of any ſufficient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, will ſo maintaine his ſkirmiſh, that he will ſtill haue as many bullets flying, as the archers can ſhoote ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, if they will ſhoote to any purpoſe to annoy thoſe that ſhal ſerue againſt them, &amp; there is no ſuch neceſſitie of haſtie charging, as vnſkilfull men will dreame of, but that ſhotte
<pb facs="tcp:26442:45"/>may take conuenient time, and the more they be in number the more may be their leiſure. Now for their redines to giue thoſe volies that is ſpoken of, I hope ſhot, hauing their pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces charged, proined, their matches fired, and al things redy (as they are euermore accuſtomed, if there be ſuch occaſion, they can diſcharge with quicker expedition, then an archer can nocke his arrowes and draw it to his head.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>But the Archer that alwayes marcheth with his bow readie bent, may be thought likewiſe to be moſt readie for all manner of ſeruices, and for all manner of weathers, whether faire or foule: againe, the arrowes in their diſcent are moſt noyſome
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> terrible to the enemie, lighting vpon their faces, their breaſts, their bellies, their codpéeces, theyr thighes, their legges, and there is no place that is free from their danger, but that they gawle and ſpoyle both horſe and man. Beſides, flying togither in the aire as thicke as haile, they do not onely terrifie their eies with the ſight, but they do likewiſe amaze the verie eares and hearts of men, with the noyſe and whiſtling they do make in the aire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skill</speaker>
               <p>Lord haue mercie vpon vs, what a fearefull diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is this, and I will not denie (indéede) but that they may hit vs in the faces, in the breaſts, and in the bellies, but for the codpéece, the tailers haue taken order they ſhall neuer hurt vs there any more, for they vſe to make our hoſe nowe without codpéeces, and I perceiue it is done for a good intent and for the whiſtling that they do make in the aire, if that be a matter of ſuch terrour, who would not be afraide to come amongſt a flocke of Géeſe when they haue young goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, but he that hath béene in place where a volie of Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket and Caliuer ſhot, hath paſſed by him, and hath heard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of their whiſtling, will neuer after thinke that the fluzzing of an arrow, is ſo fearefull a matter.</p>
               <p>But Captaine <hi>Pill</hi> to end this trifling, and to ſhewe you my opinion in a few words, the readieſt way to find out the effects of theſe weapons, is firſt to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of the place where they may be brought to ſerue, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> time when they may do ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, &amp; what may be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effects in the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſeruices.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26442:45"/>Firſt for the place, archers, are not ſeruiceable at all, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in trenches nor in any fortifications whatſoeuer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot in thoſe places be brought to ſerue, but they muſt make their bodyes an open marke to the muſket and caliuer, which are vſualy placed in ſuch ſort, that a man cannot put vp his head aboue the rampier, but with great danger and peril. So that their place where they may ſerue, is only in the plain &amp; open field, where they muſt be guarded with trench, hedge, ditch, or otherwiſe that horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not charge them, and yet there they cannot do their execution, but they muſt ſtande in open view to the Muſket and Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, who taking the benefit of hedge, ditch, trees, buſhes, ſhrubbes, or other couerts which almoſt euerie ground af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth them, or otherwiſe by the aduantage of farre ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, will without any danger at al to themſelues, eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place the other, and putte them from the ground: where the Muſket and Caliuer hauing once taken place of aduantage-will not be diſplaced neither with horſe nor foote, but with great hazard to thoſe that ſhall aſſaile them.</p>
               <p>For the time when theſe weapons may do their ſeruice, firſt for the bow, it cannot be but within the diſtance of nine or tenne ſcore, for vntill that time the archer is not able to ſhoot home, for although there be many that in their gaming bowes and their arrowes, fitted to their length, and neately feathered, will ſhoote ſixtéene or eightéene ſcore, yet when they ſhall be brought to their liuerie bowes, which are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made to indure weather, then for frée ſhooting, their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes likewiſe big timbered, their fethers ruffled, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they will gather winde, and ordinarily made of ſuch length, that very few will draw them to the heads by two thrée inches, theſe things conſidered, if tenne amongſt a hundred do ſhoote aboue tenne ſcore, all the reſt will ſhoote ſhort of nine. What aduantage then hath the Muſketeres, that may take their times to beate vpon troupes either of horſemen, or footemen, thirtie ſcore off, but within 24 with great forceand furie. Here is now a ſpecial matter to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the arrow comming in the aire in the diſcent, when it
<pb facs="tcp:26442:46"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> furtheſt to flie, but it falleth to the ground, where contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the ſhot diſcharged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Muſket, euen from the place of the firſt deliuerie, runneth ſtil currant within the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of a mans height, and al the way in poſſibility is indaunger, ſo that this may be concluded, neither can it be denied, as the arrow hath no poſſibilitie to indanger, in aboue one or two ranks, ſo the muſket ſhotte hath as great likelihood to hurt, in more then two or thrée and twentie.</p>
               <p>Now touching the effects of theſe weapons for their exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, the greateſt perfection of the bow, is to gall a horſe or naked men that are vnarmed, &amp; the arrow eaſily defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with matters of light cariage, as our barbarous Iriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that inuented targets made of ſmall wickers, like baſket liddes, which weighing not aboue two pownd weight, would couer them from the toppe to the toe, and ſometimes with their mantles hanging looſe about their armes, which was the cauſe that our captains of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, long ſithence haue conuerted all their bows to caliuers, and from that time haue ſo continued.</p>
               <p>The muſket ſhot is of a greater effect, both againſt horſe and man, and who is he that can carry ſuch an armour as will holde them out? Of the furder effects of theſe weapons I thinke I ſhall not néede to ſpeake, but this may ſuffice to thoſe that are not diſpoſed to cauill, and for thoſe that are peruerſe, I haue neither hope nor intention to alter or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; wil therfore make the more ſparing concluſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pill</speaker>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Skill,</hi> you could neuer haue concluded in a better time, for wée are come to a good towne, and I holde it beſt that wée ride no furder to night. And for theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thus diſcourſed between vs, although you haue in a ſort ſatiſfied me, yet I haue ſomething elſe to ſay which I will deferre till our next conuenience, but now I holde it beſt to take vp our lodgeing for this night.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Skil</speaker>
               <p>It is a very good motion, captaine <hi>Pil,</hi> and leade you the way to what Inne you are beſt acquainted at, and I will follow you.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26442:46"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
